<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The paradise of the soul: or, A little treatise of vertues. Made by Albert the Great, Bishop of Ratisbon, who died in the year 1280. Translated out of Latin into English, by N.N.</title>
            <title>Paradisus animae. English.</title>
            <author>Albertus, Magnus, Saint, 1193?-1280.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 126 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A875H</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6662</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834123</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834123</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38619</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26623)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38619)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 1772:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The paradise of the soul: or, A little treatise of vertues. Made by Albert the Great, Bishop of Ratisbon, who died in the year 1280. Translated out of Latin into English, by N.N.</title>
                  <title>Paradisus animae. English.</title>
                  <author>Albertus, Magnus, Saint, 1193?-1280.</author>
                  <author>N. N.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 240 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Brooks,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: De adhærendo Deo.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Virtues --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Catholic authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38619:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38619:1"/>
            <p>THE PARADISE OF THE SOUL: OR, A Little TREATISE OF VERTUES.</p>
            <p>Made by <hi>Albert</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ratisbon,</hi> who died in the Year 1280.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of <hi>Latin</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>N. N.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>William Brooks,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38619:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38619:2"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>TO excite thee to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of this Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Treatiſe of <hi>Albertus Magnus,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>the Nature of true Chriſtian Vertues,</hi> I ſhall only ſay of it, 'tis the <hi>Work</hi> of a <hi>Great Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> and a <hi>Great Saint;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:38619:3"/>and although <hi>Small</hi> in Bulk, yet extremely <hi>Big</hi> in its Intrinſick <hi>Worth</hi> and <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue;</hi> in a word, it is its own <hi>beſt Encomium,</hi> and needs not the Tranſlator's <hi>Recommendation.</hi> The <hi>Scope</hi> and <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Author</hi> is declared in his <hi>Preface;</hi> and how <hi>ſolidly</hi> and <hi>proficuouſly,</hi> what is deſign'd is by <hi>Him</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, each Chapter is a <hi>ſpeaking Demonſtration;</hi> Read then <hi>underſtanding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:38619:3"/>meditate <hi>frequently,</hi> practiſe <hi>ſedulouſly,</hi> and, allured with the all-raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beauty of <hi>true Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> remember ſeriouſly, that ſince it is impoſſible to be <hi>eternally happy</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Them,</hi> (though not <hi>rigorouſly</hi> requiſite in that <hi>Heroick</hi> degree as here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciphered) it ought to be thy <hi>Grand Concern</hi> to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for <hi>them</hi> daily at the <hi>Throne of Grace,</hi> that thou mayeſt not be <hi>delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:38619:4"/>as, alas! infinite <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate Chriſtians</hi> are, with <hi>falſe Shadows,</hi> but really by <hi>Grace,</hi> be poſſeſs'd of all thoſe <hi>True Vertues,</hi> ſo <hi>fully,</hi> and with ſuch <hi>Maſterly</hi> ſtroaks, tho' in plain and humble Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage deſcribed in this Tract.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:38619:4"/>
            <head>AN INDEX OF THE CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF the Love of God and our Neighbour.</hi> Chap. 1. p. 5.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Humility.</hi> ch. 2. p. 14.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Obedience.</hi> ch. 3. p. 19.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Patience.</hi> ch. 4. p. 28.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Poverty.</hi> ch. 5. p. 34.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Chaſtity.</hi> ch. 6. p. 39.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Abſtinence.</hi> ch. 7. p. 46.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Prudence.</hi> ch. 8. p. 53.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Fortitude.</hi> ch. 9. p. 59.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Juſtice.</hi> ch. 10. p. 63.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Temperance.</hi> ch. 11. p. 68.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:38619:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Compaſſion.</hi> ch. 12. p. 74.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Peace.</hi> ch. 13. p. 79.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Mercy.</hi> ch. 14. p. 84.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Concord.</hi> ch. 15. p. 90.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Conſtancy.</hi> ch. 16. p. 95.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Liberality.</hi> ch. 17. p. 100.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Truth.</hi> ch. 18. p. 105.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Meekneſs.</hi> ch. 19. p. 109.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Faith.</hi> ch. 20. p. 112.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Hope.</hi> ch. 21. p. 117.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Fear.</hi> ch. 22. p. 122.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Joy.</hi> ch. 23. p. 128.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Sadneſs.</hi> ch. 24. p. 134.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Gratitude.</hi> ch. 25. p. 139.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Zeal of Souls.</hi> ch. 26. p. 144.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Liberty.</hi> ch. 27. p. 150.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Religion.</hi> ch. 28. p. 155.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Maturity.</hi> ch. 29. p. 162.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Simplicity.</hi> ch. 30. p. 166.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Silence.</hi> ch. 31. p. 171.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Solitude.</hi> ch. 32. p. 177.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Contemplation.</hi> ch. 33. p. 182.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Diſcretion.</hi> ch. 34. p. 192.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Congratulation.</hi> ch. 35. p. 199.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:38619:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Confidence.</hi> ch. 36. p.. 203.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Contempt of the World.</hi> ch. 37. p. 212.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Mortification.</hi> ch. 38. p. 217.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Contrition.</hi> ch. 39. p. 221.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Confeſſion.</hi> ch. 40. p. 227.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Penance.</hi> ch. 41. p. 232.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Perſeverance.</hi> ch. 42. p. 236.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Epilogue, containing the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of</hi> Albert. p. 239.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:38619:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38619:6"/>
            <head>THE PARADISE OF THE SOUL.</head>
            <div type="prologue">
               <head>THE PROLOG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E.</head>
               <p>THERE are certain Vices which frequently aſſume the ſemblance of Vertues, to the end that they may be believed to be Vertues, when indeed they are Vices. So Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is reputed Juſtice: Soureneſs of mind is called Maturity: A jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Talkativeneſs paſſes for Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fability:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38619:7"/>Diſſoluteneſs is deemed Spiritual chearfulneſs of Heart: Slothfulneſs, or inordinate Sadneſs, is judged to be a Moral Gravity: A torpid Tepidity is thought to be Diſcretion: Superfluous Ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning goes for Neatneſs and Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs: Exceſs in Diet and Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue is called Gentility: Prodiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is ſtiled Liberality: Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs is Providence: Obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in Opinion is Conſtancy: Craftineſs is Prudence: Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is Sanctity: a negligent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concernedneſs is Meekneſs: The Curious man is reputed circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect: The Vain-glorious, Noble-ſpirited: Preſumption is called Hope: Carnal Love is judged Charity: a malapert Accuſer or Corrector, is ſaid to be a Zealot of Juſtice: the Diſſembler is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Patient: the puſillanimous to correct, is benign, meek, or peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38619:7"/>able: and ſo of the reſt. But as nothing of Value can be bought with falſe moneys, ſo neither is the Kingdom of Heaven to be had for falſe Vertues.</p>
               <p>There are alſo certain Natural Vertues, which Men have by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: as a Natural Humility, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity, Modeſty, Bounty, Mercy, Patience. But theſe alſo and ſuch like, do not deſerve an Eternal Reward, or the Kingdom of God, but only ſuch Vertues as are free Gifts or Graces.</p>
               <p>For there are certain gratuit Vertues, which Fools judge to be Vices. So Juſtice is judged to be Severity: Maturity, amongſt them, is reputed Soureneſs of Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Providence is called Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs: Conſtancy is called Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy: and ſo of all the reſt above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned. In like manner, that which is done out of Humility, is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38619:8"/>ſaid to be done out of Vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: What is done out of Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is ſaid to be done out of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and Vanity: What is done out of a Zeal of Juſtice, is ſaid to be done out of a deſire of Revenge: What is done out of Charity, they ſay is done out of Malice and Hatred: What is done out of Spiritual Love, they ſay is done out of Carnal Love: What is done with a pure Intention, they ſay is done for Temporal Ends: and ſo of other Vertues.</p>
               <p>Seeing then it is hard to diſcern betwixt Vice and Vertue; and ſeeing there are certain degrees in all Vertues, which are firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into the Soul by the mere Bounty of God; and being infuſed, are more deeply radicated and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and in time perfected; we ſhall nicely and throughly exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, which are the true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38619:8"/>Vertues of the Soul, by which alone we are made accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto God. And we ſhall firſt ſpeak of Love or Charity, which is the Mother and Ornament of all Vertues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of True Love of God, and our Neighbour.</head>
               <p>OUR Love of God is true and perfect, when the Soul with all its Forces, fervorouſly poures it ſelf out upon God, ſeeking in him no Advantage, Temporal or Eternal; but is affected towards him only for his innate Goodneſs, Sanctity, Perfection and Beatitude; For the delicate Soul, does, as it were, abhorr to love God by way of Profit or Reward. Even as God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38619:9"/>with all his Force poures out him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon the Soul of man, never expecting any Profit from it, but deſiring to communicate to it his own natural Beatitude: But if I love God becauſe he is good to me, and upon this account eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, that he may communicate his Happineſs to me, I am convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to have a Natural and an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Love.</p>
               <p>The inductive or motive to true Love is, a true acknowledgment of God to be what he is; for in him is the matter of all Love: to wit, Excellency, Sanctity, Power, Wiſdom, Bounty, Beauty, Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Moreover, Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, immenſe, uninterrupted, and moſt faithful Love to us, is indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of true Charity.</p>
               <p>Our Lord, in St. <hi>John, ch.</hi> 14 gives us an Argument or ſign of true Charity, ſaying, <hi>He who has
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38619:9"/>my Commandments, and keeps them, he it is who loves me.</hi> Which St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> teſtifies, ſaying, <hi>So much we love God, as we obſerve his Precepts.</hi> The ſame is to be underſtood of voluntary Vows, which have an equal Obligation with Precepts. St. <hi>Gregory</hi> alſo bears witneſs to our Lord, <hi>Return,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>my dear Brethren, inwardly to your ſelves: Ask your ſelves, if indeed you love God. Yet let no body believe himſelf, whatſoever his mind ſhall anſwer him, without the atteſtation of his Works. Let the Tongue, Mind, and Life be asked concerning the Love of your Creator. The Love of God is never idle. For if it be, it works great things: but if it refuſe to work, it is not Love.</hi> But this Execution of Works, and Obſervation of God's Commandments, muſt be purified by the Intention, and muſt be done neither for fear of Puniſhment, nor
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38619:10"/>for love of Reward; as St. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> teſtifies. He loves God, not who therefore keeps the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, becauſe he is compelled thereunto, either by the greatneſs of Puniſhment, or by the greedy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Reward; but becauſe that which is commanded is honeſt, and the very beſt.</p>
               <p>There are alſo two other ſigns of a ſincere Love to God; to wit, when a man congratulates with God in all things which pleaſe him, by whomſoever, at whatſoever time, and in whatſoever place they are done. For a natural Love deſerves no praiſe from God, becauſe it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes reflects it ſelf upon it ſelf, and ſeeks its own commodity: but the gratuitous, or free Love, only is praiſe-worthy, which always is carried out of it ſelf into another. A ſecond ſign is, when a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doles with God in all things which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38619:10"/>diſpleaſe him, by whomſoever, at whatſoever time, and in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever place they are done.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of true Love of our Neighbour.</head>
                  <p>True Love to ones Neighbour, is to love ones Neighbour as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Friend and Enemy, as St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> ſays. To love ones Neighbour as himſelf, is to love him in God, to God, and for God. Thus every one ought to love his Neighbour as himſelf: As he deſires all good to himſelf and flies all Evil, ſo let him do to his Neighbour. Or thus, As every one loves his own proper Good, in Body and Soul, in Goods, and good Name; and as every one in theſe four, flies, and hates his own proper Evil and Dammage; ſo every one ought in theſe to love all the good, and hate all the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage both of Friend and Enemy.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38619:11"/>Though no body is bound by way of Precept to be moved ſo much, or ſo ardently, to his Neighbour as to himſelf.</p>
                  <p>True Charity cannot be known by our Love of our Friends; <hi>For even the Publicans love thoſe who love them,</hi> Matt. 5. But true Charity is underſtood by our love of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. To love him that loves us, is but Nature; but to love one who does not love us, is the work of Grace. But true Charity to our Neighbour is yet more excellently underſtood in the Gloſs upon St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> which ſays, To love one that loves us is Nature, but by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and Courteſies to draw one to love, who loves us not, is Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. And although no body be bound by Precept to love ſo much and ſo fervently his Enemy as his Friend; yet happy were he, and highly Perfect, who could love as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38619:11"/>much, yea more, and do works of Charity for his Enemy as for his Friend; for him that corrects and reproves him, as for him that flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters him; for him that diſpraiſes him, as for him that praiſes him; becauſe, as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſays, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing makes us ſo like unto God, as to be courteous to thoſe who malign and hurt us.</hi> And it is certain, we might get greater Grace out of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution than out of Favour, if we knew how to uſe it aright; as the Enemies of the Martyrs profited them more to Eternal Glory than did their Friends.</p>
                  <p>Nature ought to move us to the love of our Neighbour, becauſe <hi>every living Creature loves his like: and ſo ſhould every man his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> Eccleſ. 13.19. And becauſe the Image of God is in him, and it is commanded us ſo to do in the Holy Scripture.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:38619:12"/>
                  <p>The ſigns of true Charity to our Neighbour, are, Truly to condole, as well with Enemies as with Friends, in all their Adverſities: Truly, and from the heart to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce with them in every thing that happens proſperous unto them.</p>
                  <p>The ſigns of true Hatred to our Neighbour are, when we think of him with Regret, when we ſee him with ſadneſs of heart, when we ſpeak with him, or of him, or hear others ſpeak of him with bitterneſs of mind; when we hinder, as much as we can, all his Good, and that which is profitable unto him; when we diminiſh and pervert the good which is in him. Our Lord Jeſus did not ſo to his Traytor <hi>Judas,</hi> who, in the very time of his Treaſon, fed him with his own Body and Blood, together with his other beloved Apoſtles: and in the very place where he betrayed him, refuſing not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38619:12"/>to be kiſs'd by him, moſt courteouſly ſaluted him; grieving more for his Evil, than for his own incommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as ſayes St. <hi>Hierom.</hi> But it is wonderful that any one can flatter himſelf as if he loved his Brother, when he has theſe ſigns of Hatred in his Heart. But to many it ſeems ſufficient, if they wiſh Eternal Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to their Neighbours, which they can neither give them, nor take away from them, and which they ought to wiſh even to <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Pagans.</hi> Nor will they remember, that ſeeing our Lord has laid down his Life for his Enemies, we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged alſo, not only to love our Chriſtian Brethren, but alſo to part with our Goods and Lives for them in the time of their neceſſity. But Superiours are chiefly obliged here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
                  <p>By two things Charity is cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Our Charity to God, by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38619:13"/>his Commandments, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, <hi>John</hi> 15. <hi>If ye keep my Commandments, ye ſhall remain in my Love, as I alſo have kept my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Commandments, and remain in his Love.</hi> Our Charity to our Neighbour, by Compaſſion, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> c. 7. <hi>Fail not to comfort thoſe that weep, and walk with thoſe that mourn: refuſe not to viſit the ſick: for by theſe things thou ſhalt be ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Charity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of Humility.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OUR Humility is true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, when we do not deſire glory ſhould be given us, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn it when it is given us. The hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man always fears leſt any glory ſhould be given him, and if any be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38619:13"/>given him, he trembles, and is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily ſorry for it; knowing, that Honour and Glory are due only to God. The truly humble never glories of any Grace or Glory, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he intend hereby to raiſe his Hearers to a Confidence in God: But if any Grace, or any thing that's glorious, be reported of him, he hears it with grief of Heart, and dejection of himſelf; knowing, that what is aſcribed to him, is God's alone, <hi>To whom alone, all Glory is to be given.</hi> 1 Tim. 1. The truly humble compares himſelf neither to his Superior, nor to his Inferior, nor to his Equal; nay indeed, he deems no Body inferiour to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: he contemns no Body; he heartily deſpiſes none but himſelf; and earneſtly deſires to be deſpiſed by all; and greatly rejoyces when he is deſpiſed. Such an one never fears Reproaches, becauſe he loves
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38619:14"/>no Glory. <hi>There is one who wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humbles himſelf, and his inward parts are full of Deceit.</hi> Eccleſ 19. But the truly humble, ſays S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> deſires to be reputed vile, not humble. He who loves Humility, ought to plant the Root of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in his Heart, that is, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his own Frailty. He ought to acknowledge not only how vile he is, but alſo, how vile he may be: Yea alſo, how vile he would be this very day, unleſs God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty did violently reſtrain him from ſinning, and ſubſtract Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations from him: There every one may know himſelf, and how that of his own Frailty he is diſpoſed to fall into the Abyſs and Gulf of all Vices: according to that, <hi>Thy Humiliation is in the middle of thy ſelf.</hi> Mich. 6.</p>
               <p>A frequent Exerciſe in humble Offices begets true Humility; the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38619:14"/>holy Scripture teſtifying, that he ſhall never attain the Vertue of Humility who ſhuns humble Works.</p>
               <p>True Humility is cheriſhed by this, that a man truly and indeed acknowledge, that he cannot over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come any Temptation, carnal, or ſpiritual, of himſelf, and that he is not able to do the leaſt Good and acceptable Work to God, without the ſpecial Aſſiſtance of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>It is a ſign of true Humility, when a man ſo far depreſſes himſelf, that he judges himſelf unworthy of all Grace; nor dare he deſire any, Grace: and if any Grace, without his Deſire, flow in upon him from God, he receives it with Fear; nay he judges it more laudable to want the Grace of God, than to have it, which he has ſo often divers ways demerited and defiled, and which he never enjoyed according to God's Appointment. Alſo, it is a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38619:15"/>Sign of true Humility, always to ſeek the loweſt Place, the meaneſt Companions, the humbleſt Office, and the pooreſt Cloaths.</p>
               <p>The Pride of the mind may be diſcerned two ways; By an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Argument, according to that, <hi>The Cloathing of a Man, and his Laughter, and his Gate, ſhew what he is. Eccl.</hi> 19. as a good or bad Tree is known by good or bad Fruit; becauſe all Works proceed from the Heart or Thought, as ſays S. <hi>Auguſtin:</hi> as a ſweet or ſtinking Breath exhales out of a ſound or corrupted Stomach, as out of good or bad Spices laid up in it: and as a wanton Eye is the Meſſenger of an unchaſte Heart, according to St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> ſo outward Signs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray mens Intentions. Pride is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by an inward Argument; when one in his Heart takes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in himſelf, and prefers himſelf,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38619:15"/>and deſires to be preferred before others: and when in his Deeds he deſires and affects to pleaſe men. Such an one is very unlike our humble Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, who neither pleaſed himſelf, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies, but expected the Reproach of Men, and Miſery: nor came to rule, but to be ſubject, as himſelf teſtifies, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. <hi>The Son of Man came not to be ſerved, but to ſerve.</hi> Therefore ſuch a Maſter diſſipates the Bones of Scholars, who ſeek not to pleaſe God but Men; who, as the Pſalmiſt teſtifies, ſhall at length be confounded, becauſe God has deſpiſed them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 53.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of Obedience to God.</head>
               <p>TRue and perfect Obedience to God is, when a Man di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38619:16"/>and often conſiders, what in every Time and Place would beſt pleaſe God; and what the wiſe God has eſpecially ordered him to do: and this with all his Might he always endeavours to fulfill.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Obedience to Superiors.</head>
                  <p>But, true Obedience to the Vicars of Jeſus Chriſt, to wit, Superiors, is, when the Subject faithfully and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly performs what is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Inclination; never ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting by any Sign, Word, or Deed, that he has an Averſion from that he is commanded. But, there true Obedience cannot be ſeen, where the Subject contrives the Precept; and himſelf ſuggeſts the Work, which he would gladly do: St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> teſtifying, <hi>He is thy beſt Servant, O Lord, who does not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to hear from thee what he would; but rather, would that which he ſhall
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38619:16"/>hear from thee.</hi> The truly obedient never expects an abſolute Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; but only knowing or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the Will of his Superiour, he fervorouſly executes it as if it were a Precept; after the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to whom the Will and good Pleaſure of his Father was the higheſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
                  <p>The truly obedient never diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of his own Actions, nor does he judge according to his own Senſe; nor does he declare his own Senſe to any one concerning his own Actions, ſeeing he has neither Will nor Nill; but ſimply and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely, he commits to God and his Superiour the entire Diſpoſal of himſelf.</p>
                  <p>The truly obedient does not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern betwixt Good and Evil: As <hi>Abraham,</hi> when God Almighty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to kill his Son, did
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38619:17"/>not diſcern whether it was good or evil: nor does he diſcern be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt good and better. For, he always judges that to be beſt which is commanded, even when it is doubtful; unleſs the Command ſhould appear manifeſtly to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: for then, according to S. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory, We muſt know, that never any ill thing muſt be done for Obedience, but ſometimes a good thing we are a doing ought to be intermitted for Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi> The ſame S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſays moreover, <hi>But, becauſe ſometimes the deſireable things of this World are commanded, and ſometimes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: It is greatly to be remarked, That Obedience ſometimes, if it have any thing of it's own, 'tis of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue: and other times, unleſs it have ſomething of it's own, 'tis little worth; for, when the agreeable things of this World are commanded, a higher place for example, He, who out of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38619:17"/>Obedience accepts of theſe things, he evacuates in himſelf the Virtue of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, if he alſo aſpire after theſe things by his own proper Deſire; For, he does not guide himſelf by Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, who, in accepting the grateful things of this Life, ſerves the Luſt of his own Ambition. Again, when the deſpicable things of this World, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces and Contumelies, are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unleſs the Soul of it ſelf deſire theſe things, it leſſens to it ſelf the merit of Obedience; becauſe forced and unwilling, it deſcends to thoſe things which are deſpiſed in this Life.</hi> And a little after, <hi>Obedience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in things that are diſpleaſing, it ought to have ſomething of it ſelf: and again, in thoſe things that are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, it ought not by any means to have any thing of it ſelf: To the end, that in things that are diſpleaſing, it may be ſo much more glorious, by how much it is joyned to the divine
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38619:18"/>Diſpoſition, even with Deſire: And in things that are pleaſing, it may be ſo much more true, by how much it is more heartily ſeparated, from the preſent Glory which it partakes by the Divine Order.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The motive of true Obedience is the exact Obedience of Jeſus Chriſt, who was obedient in all things, not only to God his Father, ſaying, <hi>Notwithſtanding not my Will, but thine be done.</hi> Luke 22. but was ſubject alſo both to good Men and bad, yea even to the very Devils.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, becauſe all things, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and inſenſible, are obedient unto God, and he has ſubjected them to Man, to the end, that he might underſtand that himſelf ought to be ſubject unto God. The Sun and Moon were obedient unto <hi>Joſhua, Joſh.</hi> 10. The Earth to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> when it ſwallowed up <hi>Cone, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram, Numb.</hi> 16.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38619:18"/>The Sea to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> when he walked upon it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 14. And to <hi>Moſes,</hi> when it drowned <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> and his Army, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents to the Magicians in <hi>Egypt, Exod.</hi> 7. Wild Beaſts to the <hi>Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> and Holy Fathers in <hi>Egypt,</hi> as we read in their Lives. The Air, Snow, and Hail to <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. The Rain to <hi>Elias,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings,</hi> 17.18. And the Fire to him alſo, which burnt up two Companies of fifty men a piece, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1. The Birds to the Holy Father S. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis:</hi> The Devils to the Apoſtles: and Diſeaſes to Holy men, who delivered the ſick from them: and many other Creatures to <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Egypt, Exod.</hi> 7.8, 9, 10. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all things are obedient to God, in Heaven, under Heaven, in Purgatory, and in Hell; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, deſervedly, man ought to obey God in all things, fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38619:19"/>his Will and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Bernard</hi> gives us the ſigns of true Obedience. <hi>The truly obedient knows no delayes, abhorrs putting off till to morrow, is ignorant of Slow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, prevents the Command, puts in readineſs the Eyes to ſee, the Ears to hear, he Tongue to ſpeak, the Hands to work, the Feet to go; he gathers up his whole ſelf, that he may fulfill the the Will of him that commands him.</hi> The ſame St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſays more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, Every good obedient Man gives up his Will and his Nill (to wit, into the hands of his Superiour) that he may be able to ſay, My Heart is ready O God, my Heart is ready; ready to do whatſoever thou ſhalt command me; ready to obey at thy Beck, yea, ſooner than thy Beck; ready to attend to thee, to ſerve may Neighbour, to watch over my ſelf, and to reſt in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38619:19"/>of heavenly things.</p>
                  <p>A ſign of Diſobedience is, when a Subject judges the Command of his Superiour to be unjuſt, and hence murmurs in his Heart; then he excuſes himſelf, as though he were neither able, nor ought to fulfill the Command: afterwards he ſubtilly deviſes divert ways of evading the Precept. At laſt, he perſuades ſome or other, by Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel or Entreaties, to hinder or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the Command. Not ſo <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> who went away in the Night, that he might forthwith fulfill what was commanded him: leaving his Servants at the Foot of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, leſt they ſhould hinder him from killing his moſt dear Son; and therefore deſerved a large Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction for himſelf and his Seed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:38619:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of Patience.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRue and perfect Patience is, when one endures Injuries patiently, not only when he is guilty, but alſo when he is inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; after the Example of <hi>Job,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I have not ſinned, and my Eye dwells in Bitterneſs, Job</hi> 17. And although an Injury be more intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the Innocent than to the Culpable, yet an Injury both may and ought to be borne much more contentedly, when no Fault re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morces the Conſcience, than when one has deſerved a Vexation for ſome precedent Fault: according to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who ſays, <hi>Let none of you ſuffer as a Murtherer, or a Thief, or a Reviler, or a Coveter of other mens Goods; but, if as a Chriſtian,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38619:20"/>let him not be aſhamed, but let him glorifie God on this Account,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. <hi>For it is better that ye ſuffer (if ſo be the Will of God) for well-doing, than for doing ill.</hi> 1 Pet. 3. <hi>For what Glory is it, if doing ill and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing buffetted ye bear it patiently? But if doing well, you ſuffer with Patience, this is gracious before God.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.</p>
               <p>That Patience is praiſe-worthy, which endures Injuries patiently, not only from the bad, but alſo from thoſe who ſeem to be good, and Friends; nor only for bad Deeds, but even alſo for good. Then the Soul is the beloved of God among the Daughters, as a Lilly among Thorns. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. For a Lilly, though it be pricked by Thorns, it retains, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it's Whiteneſs, and ſends forth a more fragrant Smell than if it were not pricked. So a Soul, the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38619:21"/>Spouſe of God, if it be afflicted by thoſe who ſeem to be of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and Society of the Sons of God: yet it is not provoked to Impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but endeavours carefully to preſerve the Candour of a good Conſcience, and the ſweet Odour of a good Name.</p>
               <p>He is truly patient, that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endures patiently Troubles that are brought upon him, but alſo deſires Troubles ſhould be brought upon him: after the Example of Jeſus Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>My Heart has looked for Reproach and Affliction.</hi> Pſal. 68.</p>
               <p>The truly patient does not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur amidſt his Sufferings; after the Example of <hi>Job,</hi> who amidſt his Preſſures, did not ſpeak a fooliſh Word againſt God. <hi>Job</hi> 1. but with a cheerful Mind he rejoyces in the Grievances he ſuffers, and from the bottom of his Heart gives Thanks for them.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:38619:21"/>
               <p>The truly Patient never excuſes himſelf for any Injury that is done him, even tho' asked; but commits his Cauſe to the All-faithful God, who in his own time, will not fail to manifeſt the Innocency of all who ſuffer wrongfully; as our Lord Jeſus, being interrogated by <hi>Pilate,</hi> when falſly accuſed, anſwered not a Word.</p>
               <p>The truly Patient complains to none of the Injuries he ſuffers; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by Complaints and Excuſes the Mind is ſometimes alleviated, which Alleviation he regards not: but alone with God, he bears his Trouble, until his pious and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lord repeal it by ſome inward Comfort.</p>
               <p>There are three things which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly incite true Patience. The one is, to underſtand, that for our Sins we have deſerved the eternal and bitter Pains of Hell;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38619:22"/>for Exchange whereof, we are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with Corporal Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The other is, that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by many, divers, and great Injuries, ſuffered by him for a long time, deſerved for us, that we might return his Love by being moleſted a little time. The third is, That the juſt God, according to the Length, Greatneſs, and Sharpneſs of our Sufferings, will weigh the Length, Continuance, Delight and Sweetneſs of our Joys; the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifying, That <hi>a momentary, light Tribulation for the preſent, works for us on high, above Meaſure, an eternal weight of Glory.</hi> 2 Cor. 4.</p>
               <p>A ſign of true Patience is, not to revenge our ſelves when it is in our Power, and alſo to hinder others from revenging of us; after the Example of <hi>David,</hi> who hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Shimei</hi> from being kill'd, who
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38619:22"/>caſt Stones and Dirt at him, and call'd him a Man of Blood, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. But the truly patient, rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly prays for thoſe who injure him; as did our Lord Jeſus effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually for his Crucifiers; and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Stephen</hi> for thoſe who ſtoned him. Yea, the truly patient even compells Almighty God to have Mercy on thoſe who injure him; as did <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Either forgive them this Fault, or if thou doeſt not, blot me out of thy Book which thou haſt written,</hi> Exod. 32. Such Prayers God willingly hears and grants; whence thoſe, <hi>David, Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Stephen,</hi> were heard for their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p>An Argument of Impatience is, when one, for ſome Trouble brought upon him, by reaſon of ſome inward Diſturbance, voluntarily omitts certain good Works, which he might conveniently, and ought to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38619:23"/>have done; for then God ſuffers Injury done him by Man: the ſame inward Motion can hardly hide it ſelf, but it will break out, either in the Countenance, Geſture, or Words. This is the moſt dangerous kind of Impatience, whoſe Revenge breaks it ſelf upon the innocent God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of Poverty.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRue and perfect Poverty is, voluntarily and freely to leave all things for God; to poſſeſs nothing but bare Neceſſaries; and to think ones ſelf unworthy of them: yea, ſometimes for God, and for the Love of Poverty, willingly to want even Neceſſaries; for, where there is no need, there true Poverty cannot be diſcerned. So our Lord Jeſus Chriſt wanted ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38619:23"/>Food, when he could not have Bread for himſelf and his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, rubbing Ears of Corn; who in like manner, wanted neceſſary Cloaths, when (as ſays St. <hi>Bernard</hi>) he was ſtripped ſtark naked before his Croſs; who alſo being a thirſt upon his Croſs, could not have a Draught of Water, nor a Stone, or Board whereon when he was a dying, he might lean his crucified Head. Alas, how often is Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity there where true Need is believed to be!</p>
               <p>The truly Poor deſires no tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory things, yea refuſes them when they are offered, after the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Elizeus,</hi> who refuſed the gifts of <hi>Naaman,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5. and after the Example of <hi>Daniel,</hi> who deſpiſed the gifts of King <hi>Baltha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar.</hi> He truly loves Poverty, who had rather deſerve a little Glory in the Kingdom of Heaven through
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38619:24"/>Poverty, than a great one through Riches. And this, to be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Three things ought to move us to the love of true Poverty, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to St. <hi>Bernard. Nothing,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is more dear to God, nothing more amiable to the Angels, nothing more profitable to Men, than to end this Life in Poverty and Obedience.</hi> That Poverty is pleaſing to God, the ſame St. <hi>Bernard</hi> teſtifies; <hi>In the left hand of God,</hi> ſays he, <hi>are Riches and Glory, in his right hand length of Life. Of all theſe, there was an eternal Abundance in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but Poverty, was not found there: but on Earth it did abound, and ſuperabound, and Man knew not it's Value; wherefore, the Son of God being enamoured with it, came down, that he might make Choice of it for himſelf; and that he might alſo, by his Eſteem of it, make it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to us.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:38619:24"/>
               <p>Another motive to true Poverty is, the glory of ſitting beſide our Lord Jeſus; proceeding hence, that the ignoble Poor ſhall ſit by him in Judgment, and judge the Noble and Rich. And how laudable is it before God, purely to leave all things for him, and of ones own Choice to be poor for the Love of God, to confide in God above all things, becauſe he is ſo powerful, once or twice a day to afford all things neceſſary for the Body, which are the leaſt things before God: for he gives them more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly to his Enemies than to his Friends, as he is powerful to miniſter to the Spirit Day and Night, and every Moment, an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of ſpiritual gifts, which are the greateſt things before God: nor does he communicate them to his Enemies, but only to the good, who are his Friends.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:38619:25"/>
               <p>An Argument of true Poverty is, to have no Solicitude for tranſitory things; but ſimply and ſecurely to commit himſelf to God who plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully adminiſters all Neceſſaries, even to Birds and Worms; and eſpecially to the young ones of Crows, which cry for Hunger in their Neſt, whom the old black Crow leaves to ſtarve, becauſe of their Whiteneſs, as if they were not her own Brood; who are fed either by the Bounty of God, or by the Dew of the Air, until grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing black, their Damn ſuccour them: or elſe they ſwallow down Gnats and Flies, which ſtick to the Foam of their Bills, they crying unceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Hunger.</p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe Poverty or Covetouſneſs is, willingly to beg Gifts without neceſſity; or willingly and frequently to receive them. Such an one ſells his Liberty
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38619:25"/>according to that of the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, <hi>Publius Mimus,</hi> to receive Gifts is to ſell ones Liberty yea, the Scripture ſays, <hi>Thou ſhalt not receive Gifts, becauſe they blind the Eyes of the Wiſe, and change the Words of the juſt. Deut.</hi> 16. For how is he a Lover of Poverty who will endure no Want, and receives unneceſſary Gifts willingly and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently? Yea, who asks them, and by certain ſubtle Devices extorts them, and without Neceſſity keeps them?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Chaſtity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRue and perfect Chaſtity is, when not only the Body is kept from carnal Pollution; but even the Soul is preſerved clean from carnal Concupiſcence; after the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:38619:26"/>Example of <hi>Sarah,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thou knoweſt,</hi> O <hi>Lord, that I have never luſted after man, and have kept my Soul clean from all Concupiſcence:</hi> yea, and from thoſe things which give occaſions of Concupiſcence. And this is that which follows in the ſame place, <hi>I have never kept Company with thoſe that ſport, neither have I familiarly converſed with thoſe of light behaviour. Tob.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>He truly loves Chaſtity, who (if it were poſſible) would chuſe rather leſs Grace in this life, and leſs Glory in the other, by Virginal Chaſtity to be more conformed to Jeſus Chriſt, than by paying the Conjugal debt to merit greater Grace and Glory.</p>
               <p>The motives which ought to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite us to the love, of Chaſtity are; the Example of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and of his Bleſſed Mother, and the holy Virgins, who have deſpiſed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38619:26"/>Kingdoms, and voluntarily loſt their Lives to preſerve their Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as S. <hi>Agnes,</hi> S. <hi>Katherin,</hi> S. <hi>Agatha</hi> and inumerable others: and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Chaſtity of <hi>Pagan</hi> Women and Virgins of whom S. <hi>Hierom</hi> writes, That they choſe Death that they might conſerve their Chaſtity. The Cleanneſs alſo and Freedom which follow Chaſtity ought to move and invite us to it: as alſo, the glory which our Lord Jeſus has promiſed to Chaſtity, <hi>He who ſhall overcome</hi> (ſays he, Apoc. 3.) (to wit, the concupiſcence of the Fleſh) <hi>I will give him to ſit with me in my throne, as I alſo have overcome, and have ſat with my Father in his Throne; for incorruption makes one very near unto God. Sap.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>Theſe things are inductive of Chaſtity, and conſerve it; a ſpare Diet, plain Attire, corporal Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, to avoid opportune time
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38619:27"/>and place for Impurity; which if <hi>Dina</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Jacob</hi> had done, ſhe had not been taken, when ſhe went to a feaſt to ſee the women of the Country. <hi>Gen.</hi> 34. Moreover to ſhun the Company of ſuſpected perſons. Now every man ought to be ſuſpected by every woman; for hence <hi>Thamar,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> was corrupted by her own Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe ſhe did not ſuſpect him when ſhe ſerved him alone in his counterfeit Sickneſs. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. In like manner, every Woman, though never ſo vertuous, ought to be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picious to every Man; according to the Counſel of St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> ſaying, <hi>If thou wilt preſerve thy Chaſtity, if thou happen to ſee a Woman, although of good Converſation, love her with thy Mind but not with thy corporal Preſence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the chief Preſervative of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, is to be delighted in the Lord;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38619:27"/>for then all other things become vile. <hi>Spiritual Delights being once taſted, all carnal become inſipid.</hi> St. Bernard. <hi>Whence</hi> St Gregory, <hi>He who is overcome by the love of Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Things, is by no means delighted in God; for, the Soul can never be without all Delight: For, it is either delighted with the loweſt things, or with the higheſt; and with how great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Induſtry it aſpires to the higheſt, with ſo much greater loathing it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glects the loweſt. And with how much more Heat it is inflamed towards the loweſt, with ſo greater damnable Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity it grows cold towards the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; for both of them cannot equally and together be loved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Argument of true Chaſtity is, a reſtraining of the five Senſes from the Allurements of the Fleſh, and a Subtraction of the Heart from vain Thoughts and Delights; for, from the Delectation of the Sight in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38619:28"/>ſeeing. of the Taſt in taſting, of the Smell in ſmelling, of the Feeling in touching, of the Feet in walking, of the Mouth in laughing and talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are wont to ariſe carnal deſires, which effeminate the Soul, and make it pliable and inclined to Impurity.</p>
               <p>An Argument or Inductive of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſtity is, Intemperance in Meat and Drink: for hence <hi>Noah</hi> was immodeſtly uncovered. <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. And <hi>Lot</hi> committed Inceſt with his own Daughters. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. And therefore the Apoſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. commands, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Be not drunk with Wine, in which is Luxury:</hi> to wit, occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</p>
               <p>Moreover, <hi>An unchaſte Eye is the Meſſenger of an unchaſte Heart,</hi> as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> teſtifies. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, unchaſte Words, an unchaſte Gate, and holding Chat with Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> teſtifies, <hi>ch.</hi> 9. <hi>For the Beauty of a Woman many
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38619:28"/>have periſhed; and hereby Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence is inflamed like a Fire.</hi> In like manner, talking with Men inflames Women, and a curious eying of the Gate and Beauty of another, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes to Impurity; which <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticus</hi> diſſuades, ſaying, <hi>Do not look upon a Virgin, leaſt thou happen to be ſcandalized in her Comelineſs, Eccl.</hi> 9. The ſame Care a Woman ought to have towards Men; let her not fix her Thoughts or Eyes upon a Man, nor a Man in like manner upon a Woman. This wholſom Counſel <hi>Job</hi> followed, chap. 31. <hi>I have made a Covenant with my Eyes, not ſo much as to think upon a Virgin;</hi> which is more than ſimply to decline their Converſation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:38619:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of Abſtinence.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRue and perfect Abſtinence is, the uſe of only Neceſſaries, in Food and Rayment, and an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal ſubtraction of Delicacies and Superfluities, and of ſuch things as are prepared with great Care, and bought with great Coſt: after the Example of S. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt, who eat Locuſts and the Leaves of milky Trees, which had the Savour of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and drank Water, and his Rayment was made of Camels hair, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. Whence the Apoſtle, <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Food and Rayment, let us be therewith content.</hi> 1 Tim. 6. Becauſe <hi>the Servant of God ought not to have Cloaths for Ornament or Delight, but to cover his Nakedneſs.</hi> As ſays the ordinary Gloſs upon St. <hi>Matthew,</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:38619:29"/>concerning the Cloathing of Saint <hi>John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He obſerves and loves true Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, who does not only wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly abſtain from thoſe things which are delightfull, which he has not, and which are unlawful to him; but alſo freely and purely, for the love of God, forbears ſuch delightful Things as he has, and may have, and might uſe lawfully and meritoriouſly; whether they be dear or vile. For if any one ſhould take more Delight in Roots than in Partridges, in Water than in Wine, Abſtinence from Water and Roots, would be more acceptable to God, than Abſtinence from Wine and Partridges. For S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſays, no Delicacies whatſoever do hurt us, if they be taken without deſire. And courſe meats eaten with guſt or greedily, hinder the Virtue of perfect Abſtinence: for, <hi>David</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:38619:30"/>poured out the Water upon the Ground, which he had inordinately deſired; which he dared not drink becauſe he had vehemently deſired it, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. <hi>Elias</hi> did eat Fleſh, not which he deſired, but which God ſent him by a Crow. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17. <hi>Eſau</hi> is a Witneſs of this, who ſold a Bleſſing never to be recovered, not for a Fowl, but for a Meſs of Broth. Nor muſt we only abſtain from thoſe things which pleaſe the Body, but alſo from thoſe which delight the Soul; to wit, from Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, from idle Diſcourſe, from temporal Joy, and from carnal Friendſhip. This Abſtinence is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and alſo more laudable than the firſt.</p>
               <p>There are two Motives to true Abſtinence. The one, that we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver receive the Gifts of God with due Gratitude; and never enjoy them for their right end, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:38619:30"/>to the divine Order; and hereby incurr God's ſevere Anger. The other is, that we muſt give a ſtrict Account of all the Gifts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by us, to wit, for what end we have received them; either for our own Pleaſure, or for juſt Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, or for common Good. But he who wholly abſtains from them has no account at all to give of them.</p>
               <p>A double Profit follows Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence; to wit, a Knowledge of the divine Secrets, and the hearing of our Prayers; which are both ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in <hi>Daniel,</hi> who, becauſe he refuſed the King's Meat and Drink, and would live upon Water and Pulſe, ſurpaſſed all the Magici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Sooth-ſayers in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Viſions and Dreams. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe for his Prayers the ſeven Years which <hi>Nebuchodonozor</hi> ſhould have lived as a Beaſt, were
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38619:31"/>changed into ſeven Months; when alſo he had obtained of God to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the Kings to give the People leave to return to <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> he alſo obtained for the People, when they delayed, a Will to return. In many Deſires, and in the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of Myſteries, he was heard for his Abſtinence; which himſelf teſtifies, ſaying, <hi>Dan.</hi> 10. <hi>In thoſe days, I</hi> Daniel <hi>lamented and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for three Weeks I eat no pleaſant Bread, and Fleſh and Wine entred not into my Mouth; neither was I anointed with Oyntment.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an Angel ſaid unto him, <hi>From the firſt day on which thou did'ſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to afflict thy ſelf in the Sight of thy God, thy Words were heard.</hi> A third may be added, that Abſtinence procures the Mercy of God; as appears in the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> who at <hi>Jonas</hi>'s preaching, through Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence obtained the Mercy of God. <hi>Jon.</hi> 3.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:38619:31"/>
               <p>We may admire, but not imitate, the Abſtinence of the ancient Prieſts, of whom St. <hi>Hierom</hi> writes, that they always abſtained from Fleſh and Wine, for a weakneſs of Brain and Giddineſs, which they ſuffered from their ſpare Diet; and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to prevent luſtful Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, which is wont to ariſe from thoſe Meats, and from that Drink. They ſeldom eat Bread leſt they ſhould burthen their Stomach, and when they did eat any, they eat pounded Hyſop with it, that by the Heat of this Herb they might concoct that groſſer Food; they uſed no Oyl, but with Herbs, and this very ſparingly, to take away the Offenſiveneſs and Sharpneſs of their Taſte. What ſhall I ſpeak of Fowls? when they abſtain from Eggs and Milk as Fleſh; one of which, they call liquid Fleſh, the other Blood, only with the Colour changed.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:38619:32"/>
               <p>An Argument of true Abſtinence is, when one does not only in time of Health reject coſtly and delicate Viands; but alſo when in Sickneſs and other Neceſſity he makes uſe of them with Grief of Mind: alſo, when one does not only abſtain from delicate, coſtly, and ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Meats, but alſo, ſometimes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts from himſelf even Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that he may impart them to the Needy: according to that of St. <hi>Hierom, What thou wouldeſt eat if thou did'ſt not faſt, give to the</hi> Poor, <hi>that the Faſt of thy Body may be the Feaſt of thy Soul, but not the gain of thy Purſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe Abſtinence is, to forbear coſtly and delicate Meats, only when thou haſt them not, or for vain-glory to be praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; or for Parſimony to prevent Poverty; or for Covetouſneſs, to grow rich; or for Health-ſake; or
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38619:32"/>to avoid Infamy and Detraction; or to procure ſome Dignity or tranſitory Emolument; and not to obtain Grace in this Life, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of Prudence.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRue and perfect Prudence is, always to labour after the knowledge of the divine Nature, and the depth of humane Miſery; which Prudence, St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after, ſaying, O God, who art always the ſame, may I know my ſelf, may I know thee!</p>
               <p>He has true Prudence who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours ſollicitouſly to acknowledge what is the beſt, and embraces it with all his Might; and what is the worſt, and deteſts it with all his Heart. He is truly prudent, who
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38619:33"/>frequently ponders what ſhall be the Lot of the good, and what of the bad; what Joy it ſhall be to the good to be eternally united to the ſupreme Good, and what a grief it ſhall be to the bad to be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſeparated from the ſame chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Good. He has true Prudence who eyes, with his utmoſt Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, every thing, which hinders, for a time, from the Familiarity of God, to wit, Venial Sin, and which ſeparates for ever from the Fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, to wit, Mortal Sin. In like manner, he uſes true Prudence who loves all things, which make to draw near to God, to wit, good Works; and which eternally unite to God, to wit, Vertues, and the Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>A Motive to true Prudence is, the Example of the Philoſophers, who laboured ſo much for Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> writes, that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38619:33"/>they ſhunned Cities and much Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, pleaſant Gardens (where the ground is watered with delightfull Streams, the Birds ſweetly ſing, the Trees are peruqued with Leaves, or are other Allurements of the Eyes) leaſt by a luxuriant Abundance, the Fortitude of the Mind ſhould be effeminated, and its Prudence debauched. For, it is unprofitable, often to ſee thoſe things, by which ſome time or other thou mayſt be taken, and ſo commit thy ſelf to the Temptation of ſuch things, as thou canſt not want, but with diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty: In like manner, the <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goreans</hi> were wont to dwell in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart places. And we read of ſome, who have put out their Eyes, leſt by their Sight they ſhould be drawn from the Contemplation of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy. But if any one think he may enjoy all Abundance in Meats and Drinks, and yet be able to attend
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38619:34"/>to the ſtudy of Wiſdom; that is, be in the midſt of all delights, and not be entangled and held by them, he deceives himſelf: for our Mind, runs upon that which we ſee, hear, ſmell, taſte, and touch: and our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite is drawn after that with whole pleaſure it is taken. How much more we, who ought to ſtudy Divine Wiſdom? We ought alſo to be moved hereunto, by the Damnation of many for their Imprudence; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of Eſaias, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>Therefore thy people was led away Captive, becauſe they had not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. And of</hi> Baruch, chap. 3. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had not Wiſdom, they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed through their folly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Office of Prudence is, to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Thoughts of the heart, that they wander not out of God; the Affections of the mind that they be not taken up with creatures; our Wills, that they be not averted from
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:38619:34"/>God; our Intentions, that they be not mixed, but pure; our Judgments and Suſpicions, that they be convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to God. In like manner it ought to order all our Words, Deeds and Motions; that they be done for a due End, for the common Good, and Amendment of all. For as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> teſtifies; <hi>The wiſdom of a man appeareth in his Countenance;</hi> that is, in his exterior Converſation. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8. He who is ſo ordered has an Argument of true Wiſdom. Concerning this S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaies: Every day diſcuſs and examine thy Life; Advert diligently, how much thou haſt profited, how much thou haſt gon backward: what thou art in thy Manners, what in thy Affections, how like and unlike unto God: ſtudy diligently to know thy ſelf: For thou art much better if thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy ſelf, than if being ignorant of thy ſelf, thou knoweſt the Courſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38619:35"/>of the Stars, and the Vertues of Herbs.</p>
               <p>An argument of falſe prudence is to endeavor to know the courſe of the Stars, the Vertues of Herbs, the value of Jewels, only for gain. For ſuch knowledg does not edifie, but puff up with Vanity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. To be crafty alſo in ſecular affairs indicates falſe Prudence: yea it is Fooliſhneſs, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> teſtifieth, who ſays, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>The Wiſdom of this World is folly in the ſight of God.</hi> And ſuch alas, there are but too many: and therefore, our Lord Jeſus complains ſaying, <hi>Luke.</hi> 16. <hi>The Children of this World, are wiſer than the Children of Light in their Generation.</hi> There are alſo others who are ſubtil to continue Wickedneſſes and new Inventions: but they are blind to conſider the Will of God: of ſuch the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſays; <hi>They are wiſe to do evil; but they are ignorant
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38619:35"/>how to do well;</hi> Such, as the Apoſtle ſayes, ſaying (and believing) them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Wiſe, they are become Fools.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of Fortitude.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRue and perfect Fortitude is to have Command over ones own Soul, when the Mind is tempted by Pride, Envy, Anger, Luxury, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, vain Glory, Complacence and carnall Delights; and rightly underſtanding Reaſon, does by no means conſent, but inſtantly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes ſuch Motions: Whence that Pro. 16. <hi>Better is he who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands his own Soul, than he who conquers Cities.</hi> This Fortitude, the ſtrongeſt of men, <hi>Sampſon,</hi> had not, although he tore a Lion in Pieces, and killed a thouſand men with the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38619:36"/>Jaw-bone of an Aſs: Becauſe, for the luſt of a woman, he was deprived of all his ſtrength, <hi>Judges</hi> 14.15, 16.</p>
               <p>He has true Fortitude, who reſtraines his Body and ſenſes from all unlawful Things. This Fortitude <hi>David</hi> had not, who killed a Lion and a Bear, and ſlew <hi>Goliah,</hi> but reſtrain'd not his Eyes from behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unlawful Objects, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. O what Strength and Courage have ſome, to faſt, to watch, to chaſtize their Bodies with hair ſhirts and diſciplines; &amp; yet are not able to reſtrain their Feet from ways of wickedneſs, their hands from unlawfull Works and Touches, their Ears from noxious hearing; nor eſpecialy their Tongue from hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Words; <hi>S. James</hi> ſaying, <hi>All Beaſts, and Birds, and Serpents, and other living Creatures are tamed, and have been tamed by men; but no man can tame the Tongue: it is a reſtleſs Evil, full of deadly poyſon,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:38619:36"/>James.</hi> 3. And yet he alſo tells us, that without this reſtraining of the tongue, there is no true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: <hi>if any one think himſelf to be Religious, and bridles not his tongue deceiving his own heart, this mans Religion is vain, James.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>The Inductive of true Fortitude, is, a taſte of Spiritual ſweetneſs. For this ſtrengthens the mind to do good things, to endure Adverſities, and to overcome Vices, and all things that are hurtful. This was prefigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in <hi>Jonathan,</hi> who having taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a little Hony, was enlightened and animated to purſue his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. So <hi>Moſes,</hi> having taſted a Spiritual Sweetneſs from the Light and Converſation of God, was ſo ſtrengthened, that for forty days he needed no Corporeal Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>The Office of Fortitude is, to confirm the Underſtanding in the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38619:37"/>Knowledge of God, and the Will in the love of him and our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; to ſtrengthen the Mind in Adverſity, that it be not terrified, and in Proſperity, that it be not effeminated. Alſo, to animate the Mind, that it may be continually exerciſed in good: to ſtrengthen it, that it may never be overcome by Afflictions. The firſt Fortitude St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Stephen</hi> had, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and <hi>Act.</hi> 7. The ſecond, <hi>Mattathias</hi> and <hi>Eleazarus,</hi> 2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 6. <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>Daniel, Job</hi> 1. <hi>Dan.</hi> I. The third <hi>Tobias, Tob.</hi> 1.2. Whoſoever expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments this in himſelf, let him be ſecure that he has true Fortitude.</p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe, yea, of the worſt Fortitude, is, to dare to do many and great things againſt God. Of this St. <hi>Anſelm: Power to ſin is not liberty, nor any part of liberty.</hi> To have power to ſin, is rather not to have power, than to have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38619:37"/>For whoſoever has power to that which is not expedient for him, by how much he has power to this, by ſo much Infirmity and Perverſity has power over him. Whence <hi>Eſaias,</hi> ch. 5. <hi>Wo to them that are potent to drink wine, and ſtrong to drunkenneſs.</hi> This Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude had the Kings and Princes of old, the Perſecuters of the Church; and at this time have, and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall have, Antichriſt and his Aſſociates.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of Juſtice.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE and perfect Juſtice to God, is, a rendring of due praiſe to the Divine Nature in all things; a rendring of due thanks for all goods and gifts beſtowed, and for all Evils ſuffered for us; a rendring of due Satisfaction for all
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:38619:38"/>Commiſſions and Omiſſions, and of due hearty Grief for all Graces neglected.</p>
               <p>He has true Juſtice to God, who is faithful to him, always, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, in keeping all Precepts and Vows, who uſes ſo great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in every of his Works, and at all times, as if his Salvation whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depended on each of them; and who does all his good Works pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for God, nor for any Favour or Profit of this Life or of the other; and who receives every Gift with due Gratitude, and enjoys it always and every where, according to the Order that God has appointed.</p>
               <p>True Juſtice to our Neighbour lyes in two things. <hi>Tob.</hi> 4. Never to do to our Neighbour what we would not juſtly have to be done to our ſelves; that is, never to hurt or offend him, by Word, or Deed, or Sign, or Counſel, in his Goods,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38619:38"/>in his Body, or in his Honour; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to ſuſpect ill of him; never to detract from him; never to miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret or diminiſh his Good; never to hinder his Good, for theſe things no Body, according to Juſtice, would have to be done to himſelf. Alſo, to do good to his Neighbour, as he juſtly would have to be done to himſelf; that is, to honour his Neighbour, to think well of him, to interpret well all his Actions, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his bad ones; always to rejoyce with him in his Good, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole with him for his Misfortunes; always to excuſe his Innocency and to defend him being abſent: for, every one, according to Juſtice, would have theſe things done to himſelf. And it is ſaid according to Juſtice, becauſe a Judge would not be hanged by a Thief, and yet he ought to hang a Thief; becauſe not to Will that, is according to Juſtice.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:38619:39"/>And a Robber would willingly be robbed ſo he might be permitted to rob, which notwithſtanding, he ought not to do, becauſe to will that, is not according to Juſtice. Alſo, he obſerves Juſtice to the Dead, who does not delay to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their Will according to their Appointment; and who, according to his Obligation, alleviates and ſhortens their Pains, by Faſting, Prayers, and Alms. The Pains of thoſe which are in Purgatory, are ſhortned by Faſting, Prayers and Alms; as teſtifies St. <hi>Bernard.</hi> He alſo obſerves Juſtice to the Angels, who acquieſcing in their good Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, does not retard their Glory which is due to them upon this Account; which they deſerve for their good Offices done to us.</p>
               <p>A Motive to true Juſtice is, that which <hi>David</hi> ſays, Pſal. 10. <hi>God is juſt, and loves Juſtice.</hi> Alſo Hope
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:38619:39"/>and Joy is promiſed the Juſt in this preſent Life, Pſal. 63. <hi>The juſt Man ſhall rejoyce in the Lord, and ſhall hope in him.</hi> Alſo, Exaltation and Praiſe is commanded the Juſt; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that, Pſal. 32. <hi>Exult,</hi> O <hi>ye Just, in the Lord, Praiſe becomes the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright.</hi> Alſo, Security in the day of Judgment is fore-told the Juſt, Wiſd. 5. <hi>The Just ſhall ſtand in great Constancy.</hi> In fine, eternal Life is promiſed the Juſt, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that, Wiſd. 5. <hi>The Just ſhall live for ever.</hi> And whatſoever Good is promiſed in the Scripture, it is chiefly acquired by Juſtice.</p>
               <p>The Office of true Juſtice is, to rectifie our Thoughts and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they be always ſet upon God; our Will, that it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the Divine Will; our Intentions, that they always eye God, and that we refer all things to his Praiſe. In like manner, to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:38619:40"/>direct all our Words and Deeds, that they be always done for ſome ſpecial and right end. And theſe things are an Argument of true Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
               <p>But, an Argument of Injuſtice is, to uſurp thoſe things to ones ſelf, which properly belong to God; to wit, Love, Praiſe, Honour, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; or which are our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and are due to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. O <hi>my God, direct my Steps, that no Injustice may rule over me,</hi> Pſal. 118.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Of Temperance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRue and perfect Temperance is, a juſt Moderation of our interiour Motions and exterior Works.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:38619:40"/>
               <p>He has true Temperance, who does not only reſtrain his Heart from bad and unprofitable thoughts, but alſo, obſerves a meaſure in good Thoughts, that they do not longer or oftner take up his Mind, than a juſt time requires; becauſe, Thoughts of our neceſſary Affairs, although they be profitable, yet they are not to be entertained in Time of the Divine Office; according to the Saying of St. <hi>Bernard, The Holy Ghost, at that Hour, whatſoever thou offereſt, beſides what thou oughtest, neglecting what thou oughteſt, receives it not, whoſe Will we may always do, according to his Will, he inſpiring of us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In like manner, the truly Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, moderates his Affections and Paſſions, when he ought to hope or fear any thing or nothing, and how much and how long; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what he ought, ſomewhat or nothing to rejoyce or grieve,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:38619:41"/>and how much and how long: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what he ought to have, or not to have: Love or Hatred, or Shame, and how much, and how long.</p>
               <p>In like manner, it moderates the underſtanding, that it do not employ it ſelf a longer time than is fitting about the underſtanding of any thing: it moderates likewiſe the will, what and how great it ought to be; and the intention, what and to what End, and how intent it ought to be. It poiſes alſo our free Will, how much it ought to make choice of Good, and how much reject Evil.</p>
               <p>Moreover, true Temperance mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates the tongue, to wit, when we are to ſpeak, when to be ſilent, and how long; that is in convenient time: to whom we are to ſpeak, to wit, to perſons of good, repute: when to ſpeak, and where; to wit,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:38619:41"/>in time and place convenient: how to ſpeak, and how much; to wit, maturely, with Weight, Number and Meaſure: why we are to ſpeak; to wit, for Neceſſity or Profit: of what affairs; to wit, of Soul and Body. It moderates alſo the Works and Manners and the Motion of all the parts of the Body; that, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtle, <hi>All things be done by us decently, and according to Order.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>We ought to be moved to Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, by the moſt wiſe order of God, who has diſpoſed all things in Meaſure, Number, and Weight, <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> 11. According to this order, all our Actions, Manners, and Life, ought to be meaſured, numbered, and weighed; that is, in the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Father, to whom Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; in the Vertue of the Son to whom Number; in the Vertue of the Holy Ghoſt, to whom Weight
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:38619:42"/>is aſcribed. To the ſame alſo, the Example of the Apoſtle ought to move us, ſaying, I <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>Give no offence, neither to</hi> Jews <hi>nor</hi> Gentiles, <hi>nor to the Church of God, as I alſo in all things pleaſe all Men, not ſeeking what is proſitable to my ſelf, but what is profitable to many, that they may be ſaved.</hi> He was truly temperate who offended none, and ſtudied to pleaſe all.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, who moderates himſelf in his Food, Rayment, Sleep, and in every carnal Commodity and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Joy, admitting in all theſe no Superfluity nor inordinate Delight, but pure Neceſſity.</p>
               <p>The truly Temperate endeavours to keep a Mean in all things, except in the Love and Praiſe of God, and giving of Thanks. For great is the Lord, and too too praiſe-worthy: and therefore he is to be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:38619:42"/>without Mean, Meaſure, or End.</p>
               <p>A ſign of Intemperance is, when one having perverſe Manners, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbs and diſquiets all that dwell with him. He conforms himſelf to no Body in any thing, but that which pleaſes himſelf, that he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves, and ſtrives to have it done. He is unſufferable to all others, and intolerable to himſelf: whence St. <hi>Auguſtin, Thou haſt commanded,</hi> O <hi>Lord, and ſo it was done, that every inordinate Mind ſhould be a Puniſhment to it ſelf:</hi> but how much more to others? Such an one was <hi>Iſmael,</hi> of whom it is written, <hi>Gen.</hi> 16. <hi>His hand was againſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, and every ones hand againſt him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:38619:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of Compaſſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRue and perfect Compaſſion towards God, is without Intermiſſion to be wounded at Heart with Grief, for all the Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that have been done to him, or are yet to be done to him, in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and in his Friends, <hi>Whom he who touches, touches as it were the Apple of his Eye, Zach.</hi> 2. For all the Elements had Compaſſion on Chriſt our Lord, dying upon the Croſs.</p>
               <p>A true Compaſſion to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is, heartily to condole with him for his Afflictions, as well ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual as corporal; after the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Apoſtle, ſaying, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>Who is weak, and I am not weak?</hi> Where the Gloſſ. ſays, Who is weak
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:38619:43"/>in Faith or other Virtue, and I am not weak? That is, I do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole with him as with my ſelf? Who is ſcandalized for any Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and I do not burn with the Fire of Compaſſion?</p>
               <p>True Compaſſion towards our Neighbours in Purgatory is, to be greatly afflicted for the Grievouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Pains which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure: and chiefly, becauſe they are ſeparated in the mean time from the Viſion and Fruition of God; and God in the mean time is not fully praiſed by them. And in that Affliction and Compaſſion, inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly and earneſtly to beſeech God, that he would vouchſafe to take them out of ſo ſharp and ſevere Sufferings.</p>
               <p>The ſuperabundant Compaſſion of Chriſt our Lord to us, ought to induce us to true Compaſſion: for, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> teſtifies, He makes
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:38619:44"/>ſuch haſte to abſolve the Sinner from the Torment of his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as if his Compaſſion of the miſerable did more torment him, than the Paſſion of the miſerable torments himſelf: nor had he only Compaſſion on us, but <hi>he</hi> himſelf moreover, <hi>endured our Diſeaſes and bore our Griefs, Iſa.</hi> 53. The Nature alſo of Members perſuades the ſame; as the Apoſtle teſtifies, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>If one Member ſuffer any thing, all the Members ſuffer together with it.</hi> Moreover, there is a double Profit in Compaſſion, which ought to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure us thereunto; to wit, a ſtrengthening of Charity, and a reigning together with Chriſt. Of the firſt it is ſaid, in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> chap. 7. <hi>Fail not to comfort thoſe that weep, and walk with thoſe that mourn; diſdain not to viſit the Sick; for by theſe things thou ſhalt be ſtrengthened in Love.</hi> And of the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38619:44"/>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the Apoſtle ſays, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>If we ſuffer, we ſhall together reign with him.</hi> Rare is the Virtue of Compaſſion; our Lord complaining, Pſal. 68. <hi>I expected one who ſhould condole with me, but there was none and who ſhould comfort me, but I found none.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Argument of true Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, not only to condole with our Friends, but alſo with our Enemies. So <hi>Joſeph</hi> wept over eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of his Brethren, who had ſold him for thirty Pence, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45. and <hi>David</hi> greatly lamented the Death of <hi>Saul,</hi> who had often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to kill him; yea, he cauſed the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be taught a Threne of Lamentation over his Death, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. So <hi>Abſalon</hi> being ſlain, who ſought to take away his Kingdom from him, with his Head covered, he lamented him, ſaying, <hi>My Son</hi> Abſalon, Abſalon <hi>my Son,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:38619:45"/>who ſhall give me, that I may dye for thee?</hi> Abſalon <hi>my Son, my Son</hi> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalon. 2 Sam. 18. And in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Job; I was wont,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to weep over him who was afflicted; and with my Soul had Compaſſion on the Poor,</hi> Job. 30.</p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, when one ſpeaks Words of Compaſſion, and ſhews a compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onating Countenance, and yet in his Heart rejoyces at the Affliction of his Neighbour; or being able, does not alleviate his Affliction, or not reſtrain thoſe who afflict him; but rather provokes and encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges others to afflict him, by Signs, Words, or Deeds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:38619:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of Peace.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRue Peace to God is, when our five Senſes and the Uſe of all the parts of our Body and all our inward and outward Works are diſpoſed according to the Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Reaſon; and when all our Thoughts, Affections, Wills, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and all our Exteriors, are done according to the Ordination of Reaſon; and that Reaſon is wholly ordered according to the Will of God. But, as often as any thing is done, without the Conſent of Reaſon rightly diſpoſed, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately the Peace of our Mind is diſturbed.</p>
               <p>He has true Peace with God, as ſays the <hi>Gloſſ.</hi> upon that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>(Being juſtified by Faith, let us have
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38619:46"/>Peace with God.)</hi> who does not by a contrary Will, ſtrive againſt the Commandments of God; who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the Commands of our Lord, and bows his free Will to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Precept: for, true Peace is to agree with good Manners, and to conteſt with Vices.</p>
               <p>He has true Peace with his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, who uſes his utmoſt Diligence, not deſignedly, upon what Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſoever, to cauſe Deſturbance to any one; For, he who deſigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſturbs another, can by no means beat any time without Diſturbance. For he that is diſturbed, either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venges himſelf, if he be able; or if he be not able, diſſembles it. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, he who deſignedly has cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Perturbation, carries ever with him a Sting and Remorſe of Conſcience for it.</p>
               <p>He ſeeks true Peace, who conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually conſiders himſelf only; and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:38619:46"/>leaving every one to his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Judgment,</hi> lays aſide all tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and temporal Cares, and reſts only in the Contemplation of God; for there only true Peace is found, as S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> teſtifies; ſaying, <hi>Thou haſt made us,</hi> O <hi>Lord, for thy ſelf; and our Heart is unquiet, until it reſt in thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a double profit of true Peace, which ought to induce us to the love of it; to wit, a Sweetneſs and Quiet of Mind, which follows Peace; which ſweetneſs is as it were, a part and the begining of Eternal Quiet and Sweetneſs. And alſo this true Peace prepares an Eternal and continual Habitation for God in the Soul; Who for his exceeding Mildneſs inhabits only and reſts in the quiet Heart; as himſelf teſtifies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. <hi>In Peace, then will I ſleep and reſt.</hi> And again the Pſalmiſt; <hi>Pſa.</hi> 75. <hi>His place is made in peace.</hi> Which
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38619:47"/>alſo the Apoſtle teſtifies, ſaying, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <hi>Have Peace, and the God of Peace and Love ſhall be with you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He conſerves true Peace, who follows what S. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſays. upon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians;</hi> If we mutualy love one anothers Good and Proſperity; if we tolerate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the laſt Harveſt, thoſe Sins, which without dammage of the Good Corn, or with hope of ſalvation of thoſe who ought to be corected, cannot be eradicated. If alſo, we determine not to do Works of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which ought, and yet ought not to be done, leſt the Weak ſhould be ſcandalized</p>
               <p>He has an Argumenr of true Peace, who avoids all Places, Perſons and Actions, whence probably may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low any diſturbance. He alſo has a moſt certain Argument of true Peace, who always, and every where, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the Commandements of God
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38619:47"/>and his own Vows; as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt teſtifieth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. <hi>Much Peace to them who love thy Law.</hi> An Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of moſt true Peace is, when Reaſon is in all things Subject to the Spirit.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of falſe Peace, who does not pluck up all the Roots of Diſquiet which are continually ſpringing out. Theſe are our own Will, a freedom of mind, a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity of manners, an inordinate deſire of pleaſing others; of which, we have treated elſe where.</p>
               <p>Alſo that is no true Peace, which proceedes not from our own Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but from the favour of others. For example; there are ſome who have a firm Peace, as long as they feel no Contradiction; but what pleaſes them, that they find every where: But, when ſome thing is done, which they did not think of, or ſome thing happens which does
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:38619:48"/>not pleaſe them; inſtantly they loſe their Peace of Heart: ſo that the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Peace is not in them, but rather in others without them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, thoſe without them take away their Peace, when they pleaſe. But, they who deſire true Peace ought not to advert what others do or ſay, whether they detract or flatter them; but ſhould alwaies think on ſuch things as make for Peace: and ſo the Vertue of Peace ſhall truly and laſtingly remain in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Of Mercy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Mercy conſiſts in three things, in Giving, in Pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in Supererogating.</p>
               <p>The truly Merciful, as long as he has any thing, adminiſters ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries to thoſe who are in Need;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:38619:48"/>which if he ſhould not do, he would not fulfill the Office of true Mercy: according to St. <hi>Chryſoſtom, But,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Thou haſt given once, this is not Mercy: For, unleſs thou relieve the Needy as long as thou haſt any thing, thou ſhalt not ſatisfie the Debt of Mercy: For, even the fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Virgins, having Lamps, had Oyl alſo, but not enough.</hi> This Mercy <hi>Job</hi> had, when he ſaid, <hi>Job.</hi> 31. <hi>If I have denyed to the Poor, what they deſired, and have made the Eyes of the Widdow to expect; if I have eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en my Morſel alone, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs has not eaten of it; becauſe Mercy has grown up with me from my Youth, and came forth with me out of my Mothers Womb.</hi> And a little after; <hi>The Stranger remained not without, my Door was open to Travellers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, he who gives his worldly Goods, and does not pardon Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38619:49"/>has no true Mercy; as ſays St. <hi>Gregory.</hi> Therefore, the truly merciful, of his own Accord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be asked, pardons from his Heart all Injuries; reſolves never to revenge them, neither by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, nor by another. Yea, the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly merciful is readier to give Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, than he who does the Injury is to ask it: for, the truly Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful is more grieved for the Sin of him who injures him than for his own proper Affliction which he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from him: for ſo <hi>David,</hi> from his Heart, pardoned <hi>Shimei</hi> without asking, when he curſt him and threw Stones at him; and he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited others from killing of him, ſaying, <hi>Permit him to curſe, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Command of the Lord.</hi> If perhaps the Lord may look upon my Affliction, and may render me good for this days curſing, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. So <hi>Joſeph</hi> forgave his Brethren be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:38619:49"/>they asked him, weeping over every one of them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.</p>
               <p>Nor does even all this ſatisfie the truly Merciful, unleſs he do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo obtain of God, by his Prayers, Pardon for thoſe who injure him. So <hi>Moſes</hi> obtained Pardon for the <hi>Jews,</hi> who went about to ſtone him; ſaying, <hi>Either pardon them this Fault, or if thou do'ſt not, blot me out of thy Book, which thou haſt written, Exod.</hi> 32. So St. <hi>Stephen</hi> for thoſe who ſtoned him; and our Lord Jeſus for thoſe who crucified him, obtained Grace and Pardon, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. <hi>Luke</hi> 23. Both of them ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Forgive them, for they know not what they do.</hi> Where the Doers of Injury are greatly excuſed; as if they ſhould ſay, they have no Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, for they know not what they do; and therefore what they do, is not deſervedly to be imputed to them, but to be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pardoned them.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:38619:50"/>
               <p>It ought to induce us to the love of true Mercy, that God in his own Nature is infinitely merciful, and in others loves Mercy beyond mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; as himſelf hath ſaid, <hi>Go ye, and learn what that means, I will have Mercy and not Sacrifice,</hi> Mat. 9.</p>
               <p>Another motive to Mercy is, that the merciful God will in his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment condemn without Mercy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs Men; according to St. <hi>James, Judgment without Mercy,</hi> to him who has not ſhewn Mercy, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. And the Merciful ſhall plentifully obtain Mercy from God; <hi>For he lends upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe to the Lord, who has Mercy on the Poor,</hi> Prov. 19. that is, with great Uſury and Gain he ſhall receive, whatſoever he gives to the Poor.</p>
               <p>The Office of Mercy is, to give every one a place with God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Deſerts. <hi>All Mercy ſhall make a place for every one, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:38619:50"/>to the merit of his Works,</hi> ſays <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> chap. 16.</p>
               <p>An Argument of true Mercy is, when one ſubtracts from himſelf whatſoever he can, ſaving his Life. And moreover, continually labours, even above his Strength, that he may be able more abundantly to relieve the Indigent.</p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe Mercy is, when one does not relieve the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of another, according to his Ability; but ſays to the Needy that of St. <hi>James,</hi> chap. 2. <hi>Go in Peace, be Ye warmed, and be fed; but Ye give not to them ſuch things as are neceſſary for the Body; What ſhall it profit them?</hi> Whence St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, It is needful alſo, that thou ſhould'ſt not be ſo ſparing of thine own; but when thy Lord's Goods are committed to thee, why art thou ſo tenacious of them?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:38619:51"/>
               <p>Alſo, when he pardons thoſe that injure him, when it is not in his Power to revenge himſelf; or, when he pardons them, not purely for the Love of God, but becauſe he knows God will not pardon him, unleſs he firſt pardon them; or when he prays for them only with his Mouth, but inwardly in his Heart rejoyces at their Confuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Of Concord.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Concord with God, is to be unitid to the Divine Will, in Proſperity and Adverſity; and, according to our Power, to be conformed to the Divine Manners and examples of Jeſus Chriſt. For <hi>S. John Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaies, <hi>Nothing is more worthy, than that a man be an Imitator of his Maker, and execute
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:38619:51"/>the Divine Work, according to the meaſure of his proper Facultie.</hi> This Union our Lord asked for us in the laſt Inſtant of his Life; ſaying <hi>As thou Father art in me, and I in thee, ſo may they he one in us,</hi> John 17.</p>
               <p>True Concord with our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is to Judge and think the ſame with all men, in all things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to God. As in the Primitive Church, <hi>The multitude of Believers had one Heart, and one ſoul,</hi> Act. 4.</p>
               <p>Alſo, to be conformed to others in Meat, Drink, Sleep, Manners, and Workes which are not contrary to God, nor againſt our Profeſſion, nor againſt Perfection, that we may gain more: As the Apoſtle ſays of himſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>To the Infirm I became in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that I might gain the Infirm. I was made all things to all that I might ſave all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ought to move us to the Love of true Concord, that the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:38619:52"/>of Brethren is praiſe-worthy before God, and very pleaſing unto him; As he has ſaid, by <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 25. <hi>In three things my Spirit is delighted, which are approved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and men: the Concord of Brethren, and the Love of Neighours, and a Man and his Wife agreeing well together.</hi> For, miſerable and frail men obſerve that on Earth which Angels would not obſerve in Heaven.</p>
               <p>We ought to be invited to the ſame, by the Diligence which our Lord Jeſus uſed to make Concord between Men and God; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt his Apoſtles, when there was a Contention amongſt them, who ſhould be the greateſt, <hi>Mark</hi> 9. And when the other Apoſtles had In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt the two Brethren <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> becauſe they would ſit at his right hand and his left: In all theſe things, he pacified and agreed them.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:38619:52"/>
               <p>An Argument of true Concord with God, is the Teſtimony of our Conſcience, that we are not invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in grievous Sins: Such a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony the Apoſtle had, ſaying, <hi>I am conſcious to my ſelf of nothing,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. And <hi>Job,</hi> chap. 27. <hi>Neither does my Heart reprehend me in my whole Life.</hi> Alſo, a fervent Deſire of making Progreſs our whole Life, in all good, according to the Ordination of God.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord with his Neighbour, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haves himſelf ſo holily towards all, that no Body complains of him; nor can any one ſpeak an ill Word of him. The Parents of St. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt had both the Arguments; <hi>Luke</hi> 1. <hi>They were both juſt before God, obſerving all the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Juſtifications of the Lord,</hi> as to the firſt; and <hi>without blame,</hi> as to the ſecond. <hi>Judith</hi> alſo had
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38619:53"/>them both; concerning whom it is written, <hi>Judith</hi> 8. <hi>She was in all things much renowned, for ſhe feared God greatly; nor was there any one who did ſpeak an ill Word of her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and Man is, when one does not ſolicitouſly examine his Conſcience; and ſo through an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Conſcience, he believes that he pleaſes God, when in all things he does indeed diſpleaſe him.</p>
               <p>Another Argument of Diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betwixt God and Man is, when the Divine Diſpoſition about his Creatures, is diſpleaſing to Man, and the Divine Manners and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and moſt holy Works of Jeſus Chriſt. Whence it is written, He diſpleaſes God whom God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſes.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of falſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord with his Neighbour, to whom
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:38619:53"/>the good Works and holy Manners of others are diſpleaſing in his Heart, which notwithſtanding, ſometimes with his Mouth he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends.</p>
               <p>And he has an Argument of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, who prefers his own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before others, and always en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to draw the Sentiment of others to his own, but never to conform his to others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Of Conſtancy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COnſtancy is true and perfect, when a Man can be drawn from Perfection, neither by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity nor Adverſity: as <hi>Job,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil I dye, I will not depart from my Innocency, my Juſtification, which I have begun to maintain, I will not forego.</hi> Nor can he be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38619:54"/>drawn to tranſgreſs the Divine Precepts or Vows by Threats or Flatterys. So the ſeven Bretheren in the Book of <hi>Machabees,</hi> who, their Tongues being cut out, and the Skin of their Heads plucked off, and the tops of their Hands and Feet cut off, were tormented alive in Brazen Pots, 2 <hi>Machab.</hi> 7. And <hi>Eleazarus</hi> would not diſſemble to eat unlawful fleſh; but ſaid he would rather go down to the grave, 2 <hi>Machab.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>He has true Conſtancy, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ceaſes from the Divine Praiſes; According to that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. <hi>I will bleſs the Lord at all times, his Praiſe ſhall be ever in my mouth,</hi> &amp;c. Nor does he ceaſe from a fervent Deſire of profiting: For, <hi>S. Leo</hi> Pope, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth; <hi>None of us is ſo perfect and holy but he may be ſtill more perfect and more holy.</hi> And alſo, <hi>Then we begin to be in danger of growing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:38619:54"/>worſe, when we ceaſe to deſire to grow better.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ought to be incited to true Conſtancy, by the Conſtancy of Martyrs, and eſpecially of Virgins; who, in their frail Sex, by their Conſtancy, deſerved eternal Glory. But, we ought much more to be moved to Conſtancy, by the Perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy of <hi>Jews, Hereticks,</hi> and other perverſe men in their Wickedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; who, for their Perfidiouſneſs and Pertinacy in their Iniquities, are grievouſly tormented in their Conſciences here, and expect more grievous Torments, both in Soul and Body hereafter.</p>
               <p>An Argument of true Conſtancy is, when one, neither for loſs of Life nor Goods, ceaſes from thoſe things which are pleaſing to God: So <hi>Tobias</hi> ceaſed not to bury the Dead; for which thing, King <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib</hi> had taken away all his
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:38619:55"/>Goods, and moreover, had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to be killed, <hi>Tob.</hi> 1.2. So <hi>Daniel</hi> did not ceaſe to pray, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. So the Apoſtles, after the Reſurrection of Chriſt our Lord, ceaſed not from the Manifeſtation of his Name, neither for whipping, nor for the Fear of Death; <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſaying to their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>If it be juſt in the ſight of God, to hear You rather than God, judge Ye.</hi> Act. 4. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſaid unto them, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>We muſt obey God rather than Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is an Argument of Inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, when any one departs from the way of Juſtice, to obtain the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Men, or ſome temporal Gain: as <hi>Balaam</hi> did, who, for the Gifts and Friendſhip of <hi>Balack,</hi> would curſe the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt the Commandment of the Lord, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22. Or, for fear of parting with temporal Goods, as
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:38619:55"/>that rich man, who went ſad away from our Lord Jeſus, when he counſell'd him Perfection; for he had many Poſſeſſions and Riches which he loved, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. Or, for fear of corporal Sufferings, as the Apoſtles all fled away from their beloved Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>Mattathias</hi> contemning the Honour which was ſhewn him by the Meſſengers of King <hi>Antiochus,</hi> and the Gifts that were promiſed him, forſaking all, fled into the Mountains, that he might keep the Law of his Lord. Alſo, neither the Deſire of Favour, nor the fear of Temporal Loſſes, withdrew him from the way of Juſtice, 1 <hi>Mach.</hi> 2. In like manner, neither did the fear of corporal Sufferings withdraw St. <hi>Stephen</hi> from the juſt way; but looking up to Heaven, amidſt Showers of Stones, he remained fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:38619:56"/>alſo, <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 21. <hi>I am ready not only to be bound, but alſo to dye at</hi> Hieruſalem, <hi>for the Name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>Of Liberality.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE and perfect Liberality is, when any one cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſters temporal Relief to all that are in Need, according to his Power; yea alſo, being requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he willingly communicates ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Goods to all thoſe who want them; in confeſſing, and preaching, in giving Counſel and Inſtruction: nor is he ready only to aſſiſt thoſe who deſire ſuch things, but alſo, even to thoſe who do not deſire, and care not for his Inſtruction and Preaching, according to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Opportunely and Importunely,</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:38619:56"/>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. Yea, to the unwilling, and to thoſe who know nothing of it, he communicates Prayers, Sighs, and Tears before God. Nor is the truly Liberal ſatisfied with this, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he moreover wholly ſpend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in Study, Meditation, and in other holy Works continually, for the Salvation of his Neighbours.</p>
               <p>To this Liberality we ought to be induced, by a deſire of Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to God, who does ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually impart his gifts temporal and ſpiritual, to all, even to thoſe who do not ask them; and above all theſe things, communicates the Fleſh and Blood of his moſt belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Son Jeſus Chriſt. Nor does it ſatisfie him, ſimply to give his Gifts, unleſs alſo he give himſelf without Meaſure in every Gift.</p>
               <p>He commends his Liberality, that denies his Gift to none, though never ſo much his Enemy: yea, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:38619:57"/>often, by Night and by Day, he imparts his Gifts to every one, tho' he be never ſo much offended by any one.</p>
               <p>In this he approves his Liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that whenſoever he finds any Opportunity in a Receiver, he can by no means contain himſelf from permitting an immediate Efflux of ſpiritual gifts from him: although by his infinite Wiſdom he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knows, that he who receives thoſe Gifts, will ſhortly loſe them, or immediately defile them, or fight againſt him with thoſe very Gifts.</p>
               <p>It ought to move us hereunto, that what we give is not our own, but anothers: and the Proverb tells us, we may cut large Thongs out of another's Hide. Whence S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom, Thou oughteſt not to be ſo ſparing even of thine own; but when thy Lord's Goods are committed to thee, why ſo tenacious, why ſo cloſe fisted?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:38619:57"/>
               <p>An Argument of true Liberality is, when any one cheerfully gives what he has to thoſe who are in Need, without any Deſert of theirs, freely and without hope of Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence or Return: ſo our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus gave both himſelf and all he had; and this is the top of Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Nor does it ſatisfie the truly Liberal to give his Goods; in time of Neceſſity, he offers him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf even unto Death, for the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Neighbours: as S. <hi>John</hi> teaches us, ſaying, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. <hi>By this we have known Gods Love, becauſe he has laid down his Life for us, and we ought to lay down our Lives for our Brethren.</hi> To this, Superiours are more eſpecially obliged. This Liberality the Apoſtle had, ſaying, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>I will moſt willingly ſpend my ſelf, and be ſpent for your Souls.</hi> The ſame ſays alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I die daily for your Glory.</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:38619:58"/>That is, I ſuffer Dangers of Death. The truly Liberal, without hopes of Recompence or Return, gives whatſoever he is, whatſoever he has, and whatſoever he can do, to God, to the eternal Encreaſe of his Divine Praiſe; to all Angels and Saints, to their perpetual Joy and Exultation; to all Sinners, to their Converſion; to all the Juſt and Perfect, to the Conſervation and Confirmation of their Perfection; to all in Purgatory, to the Miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and Abbreviation of their Pains.</p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe Liberality is, when any one gives that he may be praiſed by others; or leaſt he ſhould be worſe eſteemed, others giving; or that he may be freed from the Clamors of the Poor: and then he loſes both his Gift and Merit.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:38619:58"/>
               <p>He alſo, is falſly liberal, Who gives by Compulſion, or for Favor; or for hope of Grace in this Life and Glory in the other; or for fear of the Judge, who has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to give, and who will not permit the Tranſgreſſion of this his Precept to paſs unpuniſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>Of Truth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUTH is right and juſt, when the Mind, Tongue, and Works, truly agree: ſo that what one thinks in his Heart, he utters with his Mouth, and performs by his Deeds; after the Example of the Apoſtle inviting us, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, be ye Imitators of me: and obſerve thoſe</hi> (that is, imitate thoſe) <hi>who walk ſo as ye have our pattern.</hi> That is, ſays the Gloſſ. As I believe, teach and live.</p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:38619:59"/>
               <p>He is true, who inviolably ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves all his Vows to God, or men, and by Deed fulfills all his words once ſpoken; unleſs he ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times change them upon better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration: According to that of <hi>Iſidore,</hi> In ill promiſes reſcind thy faith; and in an a ſinful Vow change thy purpoſe: ſo God Almighty ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times has changed his Sentence, as is manifeſt in <hi>Ezechias,</hi> and the <hi>Ninevites.</hi> For he told <hi>Ezechias</hi> by <hi>Eſaias,</hi> that he ſhould dy; and yet after his tears he added fifteen years to his life, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 38. and he told the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> by the preaching of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> that within forty days their City ſhould be deſtroyed, which notwithſtanding, upon the humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of King and People, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſtand, <hi>Jona.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>It ought to induce us to the love of the Truth, that <hi>Chriſt is the Truth, Joh.</hi> 14. And becauſe Truth is
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:38619:59"/>ever amiable in it ſelf. And although Truth be ſometimes grievous and intolerable to ſome, this is not from Truth, but from their own perverſe Will, which they would gladly fulfill, if the Truth were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto them. To the chaſte and humble Truth is amiable, which commends Chaſtity and Humility, and deteſts Impurity and Pride, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe is very contrary to the Impure and Proud, who have ſtrengthened themſelves in her op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites. Alſo becauſe <hi>Truth overcomes all things,</hi> 3 <hi>Eſdras,</hi> 3. And becauſe Truth is immutable, as our Lord Jeſus ſaies, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall ſooner paſs away, than one title fall from the Law.</hi> And in <hi>S. Math. Ch.</hi> 5. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, until Heaven and Earth paſs away, one Iota or one title ſhall not fall from the Law until all things be done.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:38619:60"/>
               <p>An Argument of Truth is, when a man, neither for the Favour of any one, nor for his own Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, nor for loſs of Goods or Life, leaves the Truth; Nor Diſſembles, nor Conceals it in others: Nor ever on purpoſe ſayes, or deſigns to ſay any thing that is falſe: Nor goes from his word once ſpoken, unleſs for a juſt Cauſe; After the example of <hi>Balaam,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Num.</hi> 22. <hi>If</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lack <hi>would give me a houſe full of Gold and Silver</hi> I <hi>cannot change the word of my Lord to ſpeak more or leſs.</hi> And alſo after the Example of <hi>Jeremy, Micheas, Daniel,</hi> and other Prophets, who could by no means be overcome to deviate never ſo little from the Truth by word or deed.</p>
               <p>An Argument of Falſity is, to have one thing in the Mouth and another in the Heart, and eaſily to go from his word without any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable or neceſſary reaſon. <hi>For not
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:38619:60"/>only he is a betrayer of the Truth,</hi> (as ſays St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>) <hi>who tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing the Truth, manifeſtly ſpeaks a Lye in place of Truth; but alſo, he who does not freely ſpeak the Truth, which he ought freely to ſpeak, or does not freely defend the Truth, which he ought freely to defend. For, as a Prieſt is obliged freely to preach the Truth, which he has heard from God, ſo a Lay-man is obliged faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to defend the Truth, which he has heard from the Prieſts, and is proved in the Scriptures: which if he do not do, he is a Betrayer of the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>Of Meekneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Meekneſs or Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is, when for Injuries and Affronts, the Mind is not exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:38619:61"/>nor is any bitterneſs of Heart manifeſted exteriourly; but he who is injured is <hi>as a man not hearing, and not having Reproofs in his Mouth, Pſal.</hi> 37. After the Example of Jeſus Chriſt, concerning whom, <hi>Eſaias,</hi> chap. 53. <hi>And he ſhall not open his mouth; he ſhall be led as a Sheep to the Slaughter, and as a Lamb before the Shearer, he ſhall be dumb, and not open his mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence the <hi>Gloſſ.</hi> upon St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> ſays, <hi>He is meek, whom Sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erneſs or Bitterneſs of Mind does not affect, but the ſimplicity of Faith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs to endure all Injuſtice. He is meek, whom neither Rancor nor Anger affects, but he ſuffers all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly. Of this great Virtue our Lord made himſelf, as it were, the Maſter; which he would not have done, if it had not been of higheſt Perfection. Learn</hi> (ſays he, Mat. 11.) <hi>of me, becauſe I am meek and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:38619:61"/>of Heart. The meek does not provoke, nor is he provoked; he does not hurt, nor does he contrive to hurt: he is meek who over-rules bad manners.</hi> Hitherto the Gloſſ.</p>
               <p>The Beatitude promiſed by Chriſt our Lord ought to induce us to the Love of Meekneſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Bleſſed are the meek, for they ſhall poſſeſs the Earth.</hi> St. Auguſtin, <hi>That Earth I believe, of which it is ſaid, in</hi> Pſal. 141. <hi>Thou art my Hope, my Portion in the Land of the Living.</hi> And a little after, <hi>Bleſſed are the Meek, becauſe they ſhall poſſeſs the Earth, out of which they cannot be driven.</hi> Of this Earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. <hi>But the meek ſhall inherit the Earth, and ſhall be delighted in much Peace.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo S. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 Ep. 5. He will give Glory to the Meek; to wit, God. Further, <hi>Let the Meek hear and be glad.</hi> Pſal. 33.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:38619:62"/>
               <p>An Argument of true Meekneſs is, when the Mind does not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur in Affliction, nor does the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled return biting Words, nor ſhew any bitterneſs in his Countenance, but always reſerves his Mind quiet for the Inhabitation of God.</p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe Meekneſs is, when a man utters ſoft and mild Words, and ſhews a meek Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; and yet bears a grievous Bitterneſs in his Mind.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>Of Faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Faith is, to believe the Father, and Son, and Holy Ghoſt, to be one true God; and that in theſe three Perſons there is one indiviſible Deity, equal Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, co-eternal Majeſty. Every one of them is uncreated, immenſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:38619:62"/>eternal, ſupremely Good, Wiſe, Omnipotent, God and Lord: nor are there three uncreated, immenſe eternal, good, wiſe, omnipotent; or three Gods, or three Lords; but there is one uncreated, immenſe eternal, good, wiſe, omnipotent, only God and Lord. And amongſt theſe three Perſons none is before or after, becauſe they are co-eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; nor is any one leſſer or great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, becauſe they are, as to all things and in all things, equal: yet they differ in their Properties, becauſe the Father is unbegotten, having his Origine from none; but the Son is begotten by the Father, Light of Light, True God of True God; the Holy Ghoſt is neither created nor begotten, but equally proceeding from both.</p>
               <p>Alſo, true Faith commands us to believe, that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is true God and true Man; eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:38619:63"/>born of his Father, according to his Deity; but temporally born of his Mother, according to his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity; and in all things equal to his Father, according to his Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: who aſſumed a Soul out of nothing, and Fleſh of the moſt pure Blood of the B. Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſible and immortal, according to his Divinity: paſſible and mortal, according to his Humanity. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, he who has true Faith believes all the Articles of Faith, firmly and without doubting; ſeven belonging to the Divinity, and ſeven to the Humanity of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Faith of the ancient Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to wit, of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob, Moſes</hi> and ſuch like, ought to induce us to true Faith. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, of Infidels and Gentiles, to wit, <hi>Job, Rahab</hi> the <hi>Harlot,</hi> and ſuch like. By this all the Ancients pleaſed God. <hi>And without Faith it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:38619:63"/>to pleaſe God;</hi> as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>There is a double benefit of Faith, which alſo ought to induce us unto it: For true Faith can do all things and obtaines all things; Witneſs our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſaies <hi>Mark.</hi> 9. <hi>All things are poſſible to him that believes.</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. <hi>All things whatſoever ye ask in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, believe that ye ſhall receive them, and they ſhall happen unto you.</hi> And in the ſame chapter, <hi>Verily, I ſay unto you, That whoſoever ſhall ſay to this Mountain, Be taken away, and be caſt into the Sea: and ſhall not doubt in his Heart that whatſoever he ſhall ſay, may be done, it ſhall be done.</hi> As the <hi>Caſpian</hi> mountains at the Prayer of <hi>Alexander,</hi> were united, S. <hi>Antoninus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Argument of true Faith is, a frequent Exerciſe of good Works: <hi>For as the Body is dead without the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:38619:64"/>Spirit ſo Faith without Works is dead,</hi> As ſays <hi>S. James, Chap.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe Faith is, not to believe the Scripture in all things; but to think that all things happen by Deſtiny, or by the courſe of Nature, and not from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God. Alſo <hi>S. Chryſoſtom</hi> ſays, He <hi>does not believe God to be, who does thoſe things ſecretly (God being preſent) which he is afraid to do publickly (men being preſent.)</hi> Alſo S. <hi>Hierom, He is no true Chriſtian who dares not die in the ſtate, in which he dares live.</hi> Alas, there were many hereticks of old, of which <hi>S. Hierom</hi> writes, We ſo confeſs free Will, as we ſay that we always want the help of God: And that they do as well err who with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichaeus</hi> ſay, a man cannot avoid Sin; as thoſe, who, with <hi>Jovinian,</hi> ſay a man cannot Sin; becauſe both take away the Liberty of the Soul.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:38619:64"/>But we ſay, Man has always both Power to ſin, and alſo Power not to ſin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXI. <hi>Of Hope.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE and perfect Hope is, a certain Expectation of future Beatitude, proceeding from the Grace of God, and antecedent Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: theſe two are neceſſary to Hope. For, the Grace of God is not preſerved but by Merits; and no Body is ſaved by Merits with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Grace. Hope therefore without Merits, is not Hope, but Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>He has true Hope, who though he often exerciſe himſelf in good Works, yet he never confides in his own Merits, but only in the ſuperabundant Goodneſs and Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:38619:65"/>of God; knowing not whether his good Works pleaſe God, or no: ſeeing <hi>all our Righteouſneſs is as the Cloth of a menſtruous Woman, Iſa.</hi> 64.</p>
               <p>He has true Hope who offers to God a juſt Sacrifice: according to that, <hi>Sacrifice a Sacrifice of Justice, and hope in the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 4. A juſt Sacrifice is our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the only begotten Son of God, who upon the Altar of the Croſs offered himſelf to God for the Sins of the whole World; a more ample Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction than the whole World did owe. For, as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſays, one drop of ſo precious Blood had ſufficed to redeem all Mankind: but he poured it out abundantly, that he might ſhew the abundance of his Love. In this Sacrifice is all our Hope and Health: according to that of St. <hi>Bernard, I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a great Sin; my Conſcience is troubled, but not to deſpair, becauſe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:38619:65"/>I remember the Wounds of my Lord: for he was wounded for our Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. What is ſo to Death, which may not be cured by the Death of Chriſt? If then ſo powerful and ſo effectual a Medicine come into my Mind, I can no longer be terrified with the malignity of my Diſeaſe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it is manifeſt he miſtook, who ſaid, my Iniquity is greater than that I may deſerve Pardon,</hi> Gen. 4. And a little after, <hi>I, what is wanting to me in my ſelf, confidently uſurp to me out of the Bowels of my Lord; becauſe they flow with Mercy, nor are Holes wanting, through which they may flow forth. They have pierced his Hands and his Feet,</hi> Pſal. 21. <hi>and opened his Side with a Lance; that through theſe Chincks I might ſuck Honey out of the Rock, and Oyl out of a hard Stone,</hi> Deut. 32. <hi>That is, Might taste and ſee how ſweet the Lord is,</hi> Pſal. 33. And a
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:38619:66"/>little after, <hi>The piercing Nail is made to me an Opening Key, that I may ſee the Will of my Lord. And why ſhould I not ſee through the hole? The Nail cryes, the Wound crys, that God is, in Chriſt, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling the World to himſelf.</hi> Again, a little after, <hi>The Secrets of his Heart is manifeſt through the Holes of his Body. The great Sacrament of Piety is manifeſt. The Bowels of the Mercies of our Lord are manifeſt, with which, from on high, he has viſited us,</hi> Luke 1. <hi>For, why ſhould not Bowels be ſeen through Wounds? For in what O Lord could it be ſeen more clearely, than in thy Wounds, that thou art ſweet and mild, and of great Mercy? For greater Mercy than this has none, than that one ſhould lay down his Life for thoſe that are appointed and condemned to dye: Wherefore, my merit is the Mercy of my Lord.</hi> Hitherto
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:38619:66"/>S. <hi>Bernard.</hi> The Mercy of our Lord manifeſtly appeared in many things; for he Faſted, Watched, Prayed, Sweat, was Weary, Wept, was Whipt, Suffered, was Crucified, that in him we might have a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of all our Wants.</p>
               <p>We ought to be induced to the Hope of Beatitude, by the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great Love of our Lord Jeſus, which conſtrained him to purchaſe our Salvation with ſo ſharp Dolors: And that we might not miſs of the Salvation he has merited for us, he has given us his Angels for our Protection; his Scriptures for our inſtruction; and his own and his Saints Examples to point out our way, and his Body and Blood for our Comfort and Strength.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Hope, who valiantly reſiſts Evils, and is courageous in doing Good: who manfully attempts hard things, and ſtoutly perſeveres in them: according
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:38619:67"/>to that, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 30. <hi>Behave yourſelves like men, and let your Heart be ſtrengthened, all ye that Hope in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has an Argument of falſe Hope who tranſgreſſes the Divine Precepts and his Vows, neglecting to correct his Life according to the Scripture, and preſuming over-much upon the Goodneſs of God without good Works. Such Hope is Vain, as it is ſaid in the Book of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> Chap. 5. <hi>The Hope of the Wicked is as Down, which is carried away by the wind, and as a thin Froth, which is ſcatter'd by Storms, and as Smoke, which the Wind diſperſes; and as the memory of a Gueſt, for a day in paſſing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXII. <hi>Of Fear.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>JUST Fear is a diligent keeping of the Divine Precepts, in Faith
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:38619:67"/>and Manners. Alſo Juſt Fear is, an Anxiety of Heart, withdrawing a man from the unlawful uſe of the Members of his Body and of his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Senſes, and inward Affections; leſt the Soul ſhould be wholly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from God, or ſomewhat eſtranged from familiarity with him: Taking heed alſo, leſt the Mind take delight, in Meat, Drink, Sleep, or in any other the leaſt Creature, and ſo decay in its fervour. This An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xiety the Spouſe had to her belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; leſt ſhe ſhould offend him in any Motion, Geſture, Word or Deed, and thereby incur his disfavor. Alſo leſt ſhe ſhould be leſs gratefull, through any the very leaſt fault. Juſt fear makes to abſtain, not only from grievous Sins, but alſo from Venial. For by a cuſtom, even of Venials, Security of mind, and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity with God is loſt, and many Graces neglected.</p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:38619:68"/>
               <p>The manifold profit of juſt Fear ought to induce us thereunto. For it is <hi>the beginning of Wiſdom,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt teſtifies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. And the beginning of Juſtice, according to that, <hi>He who is without fear, cannot be juſtified, Eccleſ.</hi> 1. It is alſo the Seal and Concluſion of all Virtues and Graces, according to that, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 25. <hi>The fear of God puts it ſelf above all things.</hi> Where the fear of the Lord is not, all Grace is ſoon loſt, and the Conſcience is perverted, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 27. <hi>If thou doſt not diligently keep thy ſelf in the fear of the Lord, thy Houſe ſhall ſoon be overturned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Bernard</hi> brings another Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Fear of God; <hi>I have tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learnt, that nothing is ſo efficacious to obtain, to keep, and to recover Grace, as alwaies to be found before God, not to be high-minded, but to fear. Bleſſed is the man who alwaies
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:38619:68"/>fears,</hi> Prov. 28. <hi>Fear therefore when Grace ſmiles upon thee; fear when it leaves thee; fear when it returns again; and this is to fear alwayes.</hi> And a little after, <hi>When it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent fear, leſt thou ſhouldeſt not work worthily with it:</hi> And a little after, <hi>Fear when Grace ſhall be taken away from thee, as one who art inſtantly about to fall.</hi> And again, <hi>Now if Grace is propitiouſly returned, thou oughteſt much more to fear, leſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance thou ſuffer a relapſe, according to that in the Goſpel,</hi> John 5. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thou art cured; Go thy ways now, and ſin no more, leſt ſome worſe thing befall thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the ſame, the miſerable Fall of the Angels ought to induce us, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which, <hi>Job</hi> ſays, ch. 4. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, thoſe who ſerve him are not ſtable, and he has found wickedneſs in his Angels; How much more they who inhabit Houſes of Dirt, who have
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:38619:69"/>an Earthly Foundation, ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed as it were with a Moth.</hi> Alſo the Falls of Holy men from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the World, as of <hi>Adam, Sampſon, Solomon,</hi> and of all the Apoſtles. And alas, at this very day, very Holy men are thrown down, according to that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands ſhall fall on thy ſide</hi> (that is, who ought to have ſat by the ſide of the Judge in Judgment) <hi>and ten thouſands on thy right hand,</hi> (that is who ought to have been placed on the right hand of Chriſt.) Whence the Gloſs ſays, There are many who think they ſhall judge others, and there are many more, who think they ſhall be placed on the right hand amongſt thoſe that are ſaved; but they are deceived: For they who preſume of themſelves, and have not their Root fixed on high, fail in their imaginations.</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:38619:69"/>
               <p>We ought to be moved to the ſame by the Example of the Saints fearing God; as <hi>Job</hi> ſays of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ch. 31. <hi>I have alwaies feared God, as Waves ſwelling over me,</hi> Upon that of <hi>Job, Chap.</hi> 17. <hi>All that I have ſhall go down into the deepeſt Hell, and do you think at leaſt there I ſhall be at reſt?</hi> The Gloſs ſays, Conſider, who of us can be ſecure of Reſt when he is afraid whom the Judge himſelf commends. S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom,</hi> ſpeaking of himſelf, ſays: as often as I think upon the day of Judgment, my whole body trembles. What then ſhall ſuch poor wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es as we do, when ſo great men tremble?</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of Juſt Fear who is ſo ſollicitous in all things which belong to God, that at no time nor place he neglects any thing that is poſſible unto him: Yea, according to his power he does all things
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:38619:70"/>fervently; whence it is ſaid in Eccleſiaſtes, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. <hi>He who fears God, neglects nothing.</hi> And in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticus, Chap. 15. <hi>He who feares God, will do good things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has an Argument of unjuſt Fear, who for the loſs of Body or Goods, and not for God, does do good and omit ill: or do ill and omit Good. This Fear our Lord prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, ſaying, <hi>Math.</hi> 10. <hi>Do not fear thoſe who kill the Body.</hi> And <hi>Eſaias Chap.</hi> 51. <hi>Who art thou that thou ſhouldeſt be afraid of a mortal man?</hi> To ſuch the Lord ſaies, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. <hi>Where are their Gods, in which they put their Confidence?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIII. <hi>Of Joy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Joy, or Gladneſs, is to be comforted in thoſe things
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:38619:70"/>which belong to God. For the matter of all Joy is in God; to wit Power, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, Beauty, Beatitude, Mercy, Juſtice, Truth, Nobility, Sanctity, Meekneſs, Faithfulneſs, Charity, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and all ſuch like Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. And all theſe things are immenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and eternally in God</p>
               <p>He has true Joy, who has a ſincere Conſcience in all his Doings; Nor does ever wittingly tranſgreſs the Divine Precepts and Vows; but alwaies endeavours to grow better, and to conform himſelf to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and Divine Manners of Jeſus Chriſt. Of this Conſcience, the Apoſtle rejoyced and gloryed ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>This is our Glory, the Teſtimony of our Conſcience, that in ſimplicity of Heart and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of God, and not in Carnal Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but in the Grace of God we have had our Converſation in this
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:38619:71"/>World, but more abundantly to you wards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ought to move us to true Joy that the All-good God, amongſt all Creatures, has ſo far united Humane Nature alone to himſelf, that it may with Truth he ſaid, God is Man, and Man is God, And whatſoever God has by nature, Man has by Grace; <hi>For he did not take the Nature of Angels but the Seed of Abraham,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. S. Chryſoſtom, <hi>Is it not a great and wonderful thing, that our Fleſh ſhould ſit above and be adored by Angels and Arch-angels?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another motive is, that God has aſſured us of Eternal Beatitude, by the Promiſes, of the Law and the Prophets, and alſo by Oath; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. <hi>The Oath which he ſwore to Abraham our Father, that he would give us.</hi> By the four Evangeliſts; by the teſtimony
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:38619:71"/>of the Apoſtles; by the Pledge of the Holy Ghoſt in Baptiſm, which is a Pledg of our Inheritance; by an Earneſt, that is a fore-taſte of the Sweetneſs of God in Devotion; by an Hoſtage, who is Chriſt the only begotten Son of God. To this double Joy the Apoſtle exhorts us, ſaying, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. <hi>Rejoyce ye in our Lord alwaies</hi> (to wit for the Divine Union) <hi>Again I ſay Rejoyce</hi> (to wit, for the Certitude of Eternal Beatitude.)</p>
               <p>He has ground and matter of true Joy who is by inward inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration aſſured of the remiſſion of all his Sins, by which he grievouſly offended God, and every Creature, and loſt all the Grace he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and deſerved never to have any more beſtowed on him. This aſſurance had S. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> to whom our Lord ſaid, <hi>Luke.</hi> 7. <hi>Her many ſins are forgiven her, becauſe
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:38619:72"/>ſhe loved much.</hi> And <hi>S. Francis,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that it was revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to him, that even the laſt far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his Sins was remitted him.</p>
               <p>Another Argument and Matter of Joy is, an Aſſurance of Mind, that one is the Son of God, and Heir of the Kingdom of Heaven. This Aſſurance the Holy Ghoſt gives, as the Apoſtle ſaies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>For the Spirit it ſelf bears witneſs to our Spirit that we are the Sons of God.</hi> But if Sons, alſo Heirs; <hi>Heirs indeed of God, but co-Heirs with Chriſt.</hi> This Aſſurance the Apoſtle had, when he ſaid, in the ſame <hi>Chap. I am ſure that neither Death, nor Life, nor any Creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the Love of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe Joy is, to be delighted in tranſitory things; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be temporal Riches, or carnal Friendſhips, or ſome corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Commodity, or temporal Joy:
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:38619:72"/>This Joy is the Trap of Sadneſs. For when theſe things paſs away, Joy paſſes and Sadneſs follows. And unleſs ſuch Sadneſs depart out of the Heart, true Joy ſhall never enter into it; becauſe they cannot be together, no more than Fire and Water, which mutually expell one another.</p>
               <p>There is alſo ſomtimes a natural Joy, when a man thinks or ſpeaks; or hears another ſpeak, or reads of the Perfection of God: there is alſo a natural Joy in the deſire of the Kingdom of Heaven. For all naturally deſire Beatitude. This Joy in like manner is Vain, and it is hard to diſcern, when it is a free gift of Grace, and from God, and when natural. Happy were he, who could ſay with Eſaias, <hi>Chap.</hi> 61. <hi>Rejoycing, I will Rejoyce in the Lord,</hi> (to wit, my Creator) <hi>and my Soul ſhall Joy in my God</hi> (to
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:38619:73"/>wit, my Redeemer) <hi>Becauſe he has clothed me with the Garment of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIV. <hi>Of Sadneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Sadneſs is a grief of Heart for all the Injuries which the patient God has cauſeleſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured from his Creatures, from the beginning of the World, and which he ſhall endure until the end of it, as well from Spiritual as from Worldly men. This Grief ought to draw innumerable tears of Blood from the Eyes of all that love God.</p>
               <p>Another part of true Sadneſs is, that a man is oftentimes overcome in Temptations, without making any reſiſtance. For when he ſees or hears any thing in Birds or Beaſts which belongs to Impurity, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:38619:73"/>the mind is defiled with impure Thoughts, or Delights, or Affections. And when the Soul, by any of the five Senſes, perceives any thing which may move it to Vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, Envy, Anger, Rancor, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, Avarice, Levity, Carnal Friendſhip, or any Sin whatſoever, forthwith, without fighting, it falls into ſome of the fore-mentioned faults, doubtful whether ever it ſhall riſe again out of ſuch a Sin or no. And if, by the help of God, it do riſe again, it is uncertain if it ever recover the Grace which it had, and ſo great Grace as it had before. For man can fall of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but he cannot of himſelf riſe again. <hi>Becauſe they are Fleſh, a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit going away and not returning,</hi> Pſal. 77.</p>
               <p>Another part of true Sadneſs is, that manifold Graces flowing out of the Fountain of the Divine
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:38619:74"/>goodneſs come to nothing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not return to the Principal from whence they flowed, with a manifold increaſe, according to the Deſign of God. This all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures can never ſufficiently bewail.</p>
               <p>We ought to be induced to true Sadneſs, by the moſt holy Example of our Lord Jeſus, whoſe Soul was Sad from the very beginning of his Life to his very Death. Who alſo acknowledged the Sad to be happy, ſaying, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourn, for they ſhall be comforted.</hi> Becauſe Joys cannot be found but by Sadneſs, as a certain <hi>Gloſs</hi> ſayes upon the Canonical Epiſtle of St. <hi>James.</hi> The profit alſo which proceeds from Sadneſs, ought to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us hereunto. For true Sadneſs is more profitable than true Joy, according to that, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. <hi>It is better to go to the houſe of mourning, than to the houſe of feaſting.</hi> For,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:38619:74"/>oftentimes, one is humbled by Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but is lifted up by Joy. And, which is more lamentable, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a Spiritual man, after Joy and Devotion of Mind, becomes more free that day, and leſs vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant over his Actions, than he would have been if he ſhould have had no Joy. Another profit of Sadneſs is; Whereas Prayers and other Good Works anoint and cheriſh God, Tears (which are an effect of Sadneſs) compell or prick him; according to S. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Argument of true Sadneſs is, when the Mind is not depreſſed by Grief, but elevated; Nor would it be freed from Sadneſs, but ſtill deſires more. But Sadneſs, by which the mind is depreſt and from which it deſires inſtantly to be freed, is not Good. Such is the Sadneſs of which it is written, <hi>Pro.</hi> 17. <hi>Sadneſs of Heart dryes up
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:38619:75"/>the bones,</hi> to wit, of Virtues; and S. <hi>James. Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>The Anger of man</hi> (which proceeds from Sadneſs) <hi>does not Work the Juſtice of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Sadneſs, who reſtrains his Senſes from whatſoever delicacies: He does not See, nor Hear, nor Taſte, nor Smell, nor Touch any thing, by which his grief may be mitigated: He flyes alſo all Places, and all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, by whoſe Converſation the grief of his Heart may be diminiſhed. For he is certain, the moſt Secure way is, to end his Life in true Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; according to that, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7. <hi>The Heart of the Wiſe is where there is Sadneſs: The Heart of Fools where there is Joy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has an Argument of falſe Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who, conſidering not the moſt wiſe ordination of God, is tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the loſs of temporal Goods, or for the affliction or Death of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:38619:75"/>Friends, or for the infirmity of his own Body: or for his own Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Such a Sadneſs confers no Grace, but tears the mind in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, according to that, <hi>Pro.</hi> 25. <hi>As a Moth in a garment, and a worm in wood, ſo the Sadneſs of a man hurts his Heart:</hi> and <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. <hi>By the Sadneſs of the Heart the Spirit is dejected</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXV. <hi>Of Gratitude.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE and Perfect Gratitude, is, to magnifie the Exellency of the gifts of God in the Soul, with annihilation of ones ſelf, and a due reverence of Heart. So <hi>David</hi> mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the Gifts of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, ſaying, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. <hi>I have loved thy commandements above Gold and Topaz Stones.</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:38619:76"/>the gift of Wiſdom, ſaying, <hi>Pro.</hi> 8. <hi>Wiſdom is better than all the moſt pretious Riches; and every thing that is deſirable cannot be compared unto it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has true Gratitude, who thinks himſelf unworthy of all the Gifts of God: And by how much he reputes and judges himſelf more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the Favors of God, by ſo much the more does the Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his mind increaſe. For all thoſe things which thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us, O Chriſt, thou requireſt nothing of us, but that we would be ſaved; and thou alſo giving this very thing, as it were thankeſt the Receivers. S. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The conſideration of the Giver ought to move us to Gratitude who is Omnipotent, the moſt Noble, the moſt Loving, the moſt Faithfull, the Beſt, the moſt Happy, and the moſt Perfect. Alſo the greatneſs of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:38619:76"/>the Gifts. For there is no gift ſo ſmall, eirher corporal or ſpiritual, which comes from God, in which the immenſe God is not included, with all his Divine Virtue: the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection alſo of the giver is to be pondered: For, he does not give himſelf by halves or with Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he may be freed of us; but out of all his Divine Deſire, out of all his Love and Goodneſs, the profit alſo of the Gifts is to be conſidered: For he gives every one of them that we may know, love, and enjoy him, and to make us happy. We ought to weigh alſo, what it is that compels him to give, not the fear of any Evil, or hope of any Good, nor any Vertue of ours, but his own immenſe and eternal Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Our Unworthineſs alſo ought to be reflected on, who are not worthy even of our very Life; nor have we deſerved to be even Worms
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:38619:77"/>amongſt his other Creatures.</p>
               <p>The profit alſo of Gratitude ought to move us hereunto; for, it opens the Fountain of Deity, and moves God to pour out himſelf upon us: as Ingratitude dryes up the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Divine Deity, the dew of Mercy, the ſtreams of Grace. The greater Gratitude there is in the Soul, the more apt it is to receive Grace, and the more the All-boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful God is compell'd to give it.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Gratitude, who having maturely pondered all the above mentioned motives to Gratitude, reverently receives the Divine Graces; and with all his Heart gives thanks for them all, litle and great: and having received them from his moſt Loving Lord, with his utmoſt endeavour ſtrives to keep them undefiled. For how was the gift of the Friend gratefull which was not gratefully
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:38619:77"/>received, and which was ſo ſoon Voluntarily defiled and loſt.</p>
               <p>Nor do we need Gratitude only for thoſe things which are to our Comfort, but alſo for thoſe which are to our Affliction; for God gives both out of the ſame Goodneſs and Charity. Hence <hi>Tobias ſayes, Ch.</hi> 11. <hi>I bleſs thee O Lord God of Iſrael, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt chaſtized me, and thou haſt ſaved me.</hi> For in order to equal Grace in this Life, and Glory in the other, God gives De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to men, and permits Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to happen to them: or for their gteater Profit: as he permitted to <hi>Job,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>If we have received good things from the hand of God, why ſhould we not receive Evil?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, we ought gratefully to receive both.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:38619:78"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> Of Zeal of Souls.</head>
               <p>TRUE and perfect Zeal of Souls is, when one, by holy Meditations, by fervent Deſires, by Tears, Prayers, Watchings, Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, by Preachings, by Confeſſions, by Counſel, by Inſtruction, and by other good Works, labours for the Salvation of Souls. Now, how great this Grace is, Venerable <hi>Bede</hi> thus deſcribes; What Grace is more ſublime, and what Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more grateful to God, than theirs whoſe daily Buſineſs it is to convert Souls to the favour of their Maker, and always to be encreaſing the Joy of the celeſtial Country, by their frequent Acquiſition of faithful Souls. Alſo, St. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſays, <hi>There is no ſuch Sacrifice to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:38619:78"/>the omnipotent God, as is the Zeal of Souls.</hi> And this in regard of the Image of the B. <hi>Trinity,</hi> imprinted upon Souls.</p>
               <p>The Example of Jeſus Chriſt ought to move us to the Zeal of Souls, who all his Life long, with ſo great Fervor thirſted after the Converſion of Sinners, and the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of thoſe that were good, that for the Recovery of loſt Souls he offered his particular Members to particular Torments, and at laſt his very Life to a moſt ſhameful Death; as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> teſtifies: So great was his Zeal for the Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation of Man, that he did not attend his own Stipend, ſo he might gain the loſt Sheep. O! How great is the Dignity of Souls, and how great is the Zeal of God for Souls, for whoſe Redemption the Son of God offered all his precious blood to God his Father, when
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:38619:79"/>notwithſtanding one drop of ſuch precious blood, would have ſufficed for the Redemption of all mankind, as ſaies S. <hi>Ambroſe;</hi> and eſpecially, when hereby no happineſs could ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crew to him nor decreaſe from him. This nobiliy of Souls the Wiſdom of God knew, which is unknown to us; which S. <hi>Bernard</hi> laments, ſaying, <hi>Alas! how title do we remark the Nobleneſs of the Soul! which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent, the Body lives; whoſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence proves, what its preſence gave: Which God ſo much eſteemed, that he gave his only begotten Son for it, which the Devil ſo much prized, that he offered the whole world for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, who neither regards his own Life nor Body, ſo he may gain Souls to Chriſt. This Zeal <hi>David</hi> had when he ſaid, <hi>Who may give me that I may dy for thee, O Abſalon my Son, my Son Abſalon,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:38619:79"/>And the Apoſtle when he ſaies, 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 12. <hi>I moſt willingly will ſpend my ſelf and be ſpent for your Souls,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Brethren, I dy dayly for your Glory:</hi> that is, I ſuffer the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of Death. And S. <hi>Dominick,</hi> when he would have ſold himſelf for a certain Captive, detained by the <hi>Saracens.</hi> And again for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, who remained amongſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks for want of neceſſary ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Whom notwithſtanding the wiſe God hindred from being ſold, for the Salvation of many Souls.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of falſe Fervor, who in his Spiritual Works, is more ſolicitous for gifts than for Souls. Such is not the Devil, who was figured in the King of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites, who ſaid to Abraham, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. <hi>Give me the Souls, take the reſt to thy ſelf.</hi> And he who labours more for the Friendſhip or Favor of Men, than for their Sanctity and Perfection; ſuch an one cannot
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:38619:80"/>ſay with the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>I ſeek not yours, but you.</hi> But it is to be noted, that whenſoever two things move to any Work, to wit, God, and ſomewhat elſe, it is hard to diſcern which moves moſt: For example, the Salvation of the Soul, and the hope of Gain or Favor, or deſire to Pleaſe, or Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or ſome other Delight, moves one to hear Confeſſions; or to ſome other Spiritual Work: here it is hardly diſcerned, which of theſe moſt affects the Mind of him that labours or Works: yet it is an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſign, that ſome of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Inducements do more move than God and the Salvation of Soul, when one hears more willingly the Rich, Noble, Young, and Beautiful, than the Poor, Ignoble, Old, and Deformed. And when one is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to be oftner and longer with thoſe than with theſe, and perhaps with leſs Fruit: when notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:38619:80"/>they have as Holy Conſciences as thoſe or more Holy, and are as obedient, or more, to Counſels as they: and as much, or more, ſtudy perfection, as they: and as much or more pleaſe God, as they. Witneſs S. <hi>James, Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>Has not God cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the Poor in this World rich in Faith, and Heirs of the Kingdom, which God has promiſed to thoſe who love him, but ye have diſhonoured the Poor.</hi> To wit, not regarding him, in whom, notwithſtanding, Chriſt is chiefly honoured. As it is ſaid in an Homily upon that: <hi>Honour all men.</hi> It is evident that in their Works many more ſeek themſelves, than God. For thoſe Works, which have Labour, and alſo ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, as are Preaching, Confeſſing, Governing and ſuch like; although there be great Danger in them, yet every one is ready to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them: But thoſe Works which
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:38619:81"/>have only Labour, and no Comfort in them; as Faſting, Watching, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plines, and ſuch like: although there be no danger in them, yet every one avoids them, as much as he can.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVII. <hi>Of Liberty.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Liberty is not to be tyed with the Bonds of Sins, which do indeed bind us; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that, <hi>Pro.</hi> 5. <hi>The tranſgreſſions of the Wicked apprehend him, and he ſhall be bound with the cords of his Sins.</hi> And indeed, make him a ſlave, according to that, <hi>Jo.</hi> 8. <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one who commits Sin is a Slave of Sin.</hi> For to ſin is not Liberty, nor any part of Liberty, as ſaies S. <hi>Anſelm;</hi> but it's the worſt kind of Servitude. From this kind of Servitude no Body is freed, but by
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:38619:81"/>the help of the only Son of God: as himſelf teſtifies; <hi>If the Son ſhall have made you free, ye ſhall be free indeed:</hi> In the ſame Chapter.</p>
               <p>He has true Liberty, who is not taken with the deſire of Temporal Things, nor with the Praiſe, nor with the Favour of men, nor with ſelf-complacency, or diſpleaſure of others, nor with Carnal Friendſhip, or ſervile Fear, nor with the delight of Tranſitory Joy.</p>
               <p>The conſideration of the Divine Order, which would have man to be Free, ought to move us to the love of true Liberty; in ſign where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he has given man free Will, in this eſpecially, making him like to himſelf, that he can be forced by none, as neither can God be forced by any one. That free Will God beſtowed upon man, ſaying in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus, Chap.</hi> 15. <hi>God made Man from the Beginning, and left
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:38619:82"/>him in the hand of his own Counſel.</hi> And a litle after, <hi>He has ſet before thee Water and Fire, to which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou wilt, ſtretch forth thy hand. Before man is Life and Death, Good and Evil; What he pleaſes ſhall be given unto him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He is undoubtedly in the way to true Liberty, who ties himſelf by the inviolable obſervance of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Precepts and counſels, &amp; his own Vows: who refrains his Mind and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from pleaſure: who employs the members of his Body in no unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things: who heartily loves the Yoke of Obedience: who labours with all his Might how he may pleaſe God. The more any one applys himſelf to theſe things, the ſooner he obtains true Liberty and is more ſtrongly rooted in it. But who in this World freely does his own Will in all things, as much as he can, he is intangled in divers Snares
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:38619:82"/>of the Devil: and, when he thinks himſelf moſt free, then is he moſt ſtrongly and ſurely held in the Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and Captivity of the Devil.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty who deſires none of thoſe things which alienate and eſtrange the Mind from the familiarity of God; ſuch are, Superiority, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Employment in exterior things, too great Solicitude for the Commodities of the Fleſh, diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mind, diſtraction in diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Buſineſs; temerarious diſcuſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Life and Conſcience of others, excuſing or diminiſhing our own Defects, Manifeſtation or Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of the Defects of our Neighbours.</p>
               <p>Another Argument of Liberty is, a ſecure Confidence of Mind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Remiſſion of ones Sins, both as to the blame and pain of them, proceeding from a fervor
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:38619:83"/>of Heart, which ſometimes burns in the Heart as Fire in a Furnace; which makes a Man who was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cold and languid, hot and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed in Prayer: which Fervor, conſumes all the ſtain and pain of Sin, as Fire burns out the ruſt of Iron.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Captivity, who deteſts the Yoke of Obedience, who ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors charitable and brotherly Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, who daily contrives Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of the Injuries he ſuffers, who is affected with Humane Praiſe and Favor, who knowingly and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinaciouſly employs himſelf in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which is againſt God and his own Conſcience, or againſt the Will of his Superiors, who is delighted in the Reception or Collation of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain little Gifts or amicable Letters; whence a Wiſe man ſays, <hi>To receive Gifts is to ſell ones Liberty.</hi> And
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:38619:83"/>
                  <hi>Job, chap.</hi> 15. <hi>Fire ſhall conſume their Tents who willingly receive Gifts.</hi> That is, the Fire of falſe love, and conſequently, a Band of Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude follows that Love. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him who gives Gifts, <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22. <hi>He ſhall get Victory and Honor who gives Gifts; but he takes away the Soul of the Receiver.</hi> All theſe things take away a Mans Liberty from him, and reduce him to a miſerable Servitude: for, he cannot in Freedom of Spirit attend to God, who is taken up with ſuch things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII. <hi>Of Religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Religion, or Spiritual Life, as <hi>St. James</hi> ſays, <hi>ch.</hi> 1. is, <hi>To viſit the Fatherleſs and Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows in their Affliction, and to keep
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:38619:84"/>ones ſelf undefiled from this World.</hi> He keeps himſelf undefiled from this World, who abſolutely renounces all ſecular manners, and avoids, as much as he can, both carnal and ſpiritual Sins.</p>
               <p>The Profit of a truly ſpiritual Life ought to move us thereunto; concerning which, the Scripture ſays, <hi>Jo.</hi> 6. <hi>'Tis the Spirit which gives Life, the Fleſh profits nothing.</hi> And that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>They who are in the Fleſh cannot pleaſe God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, he who would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed become ſpiritual, ought to fly and hate carnal Commodities; that is, deteſt <hi>carnal Deſires which war againſt the Soul.</hi> as ſays <hi>S. Peter</hi> 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 2. and deſire Aſperities and carnal Incommodities; for, theſe conſerve Grace, as Thorns defend Herbs in a Garden: for, Grace flows out through the Mouth, Eyes, and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:38619:84"/>Ears. And, as Fire and Water can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be together, ſo neither can carnal and ſpiritual Pleaſure; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>St. Bernard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He muſt alſo know, that a Man can do no good of himſelf, as ſays the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Not that we are ſufficient to think any thing of our ſelves, as of our ſelves, but our Sufficiency is of God.</hi> This takes away Preſumption: and that he can do all things through Chriſt, more fully and perfectly, than by himſelf, the Apoſtle being witneſs; <hi>I can do all things in him who ſtrengthens me.</hi> This takes away Deſpair; which two things, to wit, Preſumption and Deſpair, are very noxious to ſpiritual Perſons, and often impugne them: alſo ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God to acknowledge, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly how vile he is, but alſo how vile he may be, and might have been, if God had not prevented: and this
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:38619:85"/>takes away all ſwelling Pride. And that God will exact an Acconut of all Evil committed, and all Good omitted, and all Graces neglected both for himſelf and for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity; this gives juſt Fear. Alſo, to receive all Good, as from God giving it; and this excludes falſe Love, and infers Gratitude. And to receive all Evil, as from God, graciouſly permitting it for our Profit; and this infers Patience. The more any one profits in theſe, the more he tends to a ſpiritual Life, and grows, and is confirmed in it.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Life, whoſe Spirit abſolutely over-rules the Fleſh, who is as ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of any ſpiritual Damage as corporal, and as much ſhuns the Place, Time, and Perſons, where, and by whom he may be hurt in Spirit, as where he may be hurt
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:38619:85"/>and incommodated in Body, and as ſpeedily takes care to cure his Spirit as his Fleſh; yea, has ſo much more care of his Spirit, as his Spirit is more worthy than his Body.</p>
               <p>He alſo has an Argument of true ſpiritual Life, who is as much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in ſpiritual Food as in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and does as unwillingly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect at any time his ſpiritual Food as his corporal, and does as order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take it as his corporal, and does as much compel himſelf to it when he has no Appetite, as ſick Perſons are compelled to corporal Food when they loath it.</p>
               <p>Another Argument of ſpiritual Life is, if a man be as diligent about his Spirit as about his Fleſh; if he be as ready to obey in all things his ſpiritual Phyſician, for the health of his Spirit and Soul, as the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Phyſician for the Health of
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:38619:86"/>his Body; if he be as ſolicitous to get the Grace, which he wants in Proſperity and Adverſity, which he wants towards Friends and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Enemies, which he wants when he is praiſed and when he is diſpraiſed, which he wants alone before God, and which he wants amongſt Men; as he is ſollicitous about Fleſh and Fiſh, or about Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and Winter Garments: if he labour as much to get, multiply, conſerve, and profitably to expend ſpiritual gifts, as a ſecular Perſon does concerning temporal goods; and is ſo much more diligent about his Spirit than his Body, by how much his Spirit is more worthy than his Body. Concerning all theſe things, the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>They who walk according to the Fleſh, ſavour the things of the Fleſh: But they who walk according to the Spirit, ſavour the things of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:38619:86"/>
               <p>An Argument of a carnal Life is, to live according to the Rule of the Fleſh. St. <hi>Auguſtin, He lives ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Fleſh who lives accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to himſelf; that is, goes whither he will; ſleeps when he will, and as long as he will; ſpeaks what he will, and to whom he will, and when he will; eats and drinks when he will, and as much as he will; laughs and takes filthy Pleaſure, amongſt whom he will, and when he will. In fine, whatſoever is ſweet to his Smell, he ſeeks it; whatſoever is ſoft to his ſenſe of touching, whatſoever is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful to his Eyes, whatſoever is pleaſing to his Body, he exerciſes and follows it, as he will, and when he will; becauſe he carnally wills all things lawful and unlawful. He is delighted in fine Cloaths, Horſes, and Arms, as he will and when he will. And ſo he lives and is delighted, not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, but carnally; and fulfills
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:38619:87"/>all the deſires of the Fleſh, as he will and when he will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Argument of a carnal Life is, Liberty of Tongue, whence follows a Diſtraction of Heart; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that, <hi>James</hi> 1. <hi>If any man think himſelf to be religious, not bridling his Tongue, but ſeducing his own Heart, this mans Religion is vain.</hi> Therefore it is written, <hi>Prov</hi> 21. <hi>He who keeps his Mouth and his Tongue, keeps his Soul from Straits,</hi> chap. 18. <hi>Death and Life are in the Power of the Tongue.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIX. <hi>Of Maturity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Maturity is, when all the Affections and Forces of the Soul are unanimouſly gathered up into God. Hereby the Mind is reſtrained from Vanity, and the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:38619:87"/>five Senſes from their Allurements: but, when the Soul recedes from that bleſſed Union, forthwith it is entangled with diverſe Vanities; for, all things under Heaven are Vanity; as ſays <hi>Eccleſiaſtes, ch.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>The moſt holy Example of our Lord Jeſus, ought to induce us to true Maturity; concerning whoſe Seriouſneſs, St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> writes thus; <hi>We read that our Lord Jeſus was ſad, wept, was weary from travelling, ſuffered Reproaches and Injuries, Spittle, Whips, the Croſs: but, we never read that he laughed, or enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Proſperity of this Life.</hi> Hence all the Elect rejoyce in themſelves, when they begin to be wearied with the Adverſities of the World, and not to be vainly deceived with any of it's Proſperities, knowing that there is another Life to follow. Alſo, becauſe the Holy Scripture much diſpraiſes Diſſolution and
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:38619:88"/>Laughter; according to that, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 2. <hi>I looked upon Laughter as an Error; and to Joy I ſaid, why art thou in vain deceived?</hi> And Prov. 14. <hi>Laughter ſhall be mingled with Grief, and Joy ends in mourning.</hi> And the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks thus to the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30. <hi>Thou haſt hated thoſe who occupy themſelves in deceitful Vanities without Profit.</hi> And eſpecially, the Commination of our Lord Jeſus, <hi>Luke</hi> 6. <hi>Woe unto you who now laugh, becauſe ye ſhall lament and weep.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, becauſe it much withdraws any one from the Familiarity of God, and obſtructs the Perception of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Graces.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity, who neither by idle Words, nor by Deeds, nor Signs, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Gate, nor by any other Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, provokes others to Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but always, in himſelf and others, from his Heart deteſts Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluteneſs.
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:38619:88"/>He avoids all places where are occaſions of Levity, and all diſſolute Company, that he may conſerve Maturity; knowing, <hi>That he who will touch Pitch ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed thereby, Eccleſ.</hi> 13. And he who converſes with diſſolute Perſons, will not avoid Diſſoluteneſs. Such an one was B. <hi>Job,</hi> who was ſo mature and ſober, that diſſolute Perſons avoided his Preſence; as he himſelf ſays, <hi>chap.</hi> 29. <hi>The Young men ſaw me, and hid themſelves.</hi> And he had ſuch a cuſtom of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity, that if the contrary were ſeen in him, no body would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it: whence he ſays in the ſame Chapter, <hi>If at any time I laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at them they did not believe me: and the light of my Countenance did not fall upon the Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has an Argument of Levity, who is prone to laugh, who is jeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Words, diſſolute in his
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:38619:89"/>Manners, a frequenter of diſſolute Places and Company, and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dwells with ſuch; who ſhuns grave and mature Perſons, the ſight of them is offenſive to him, and he believes the Infirmity of his Body proceeds from Sobriety. Such an one is deſcribed in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> ch. 11. <hi>Rejoyce O Young man in thy tender Age, and let thy Heart be joyful in the days of thy Youth; and walk in the ways of thy Heart, and in the ſight of thy Eyes; and know, that for all theſe things God will bring thee into Judgment.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXX. <hi>Of Simplicity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE and perfect Simplicity is, to hurt no Body, and to do Good to every one; as ſays the Gloſſ. upon the Parables. This
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:38619:89"/>is the firſt Vertue for which <hi>Job</hi> is commended, <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>There was a man in the Land of</hi> Hus, <hi>whoſe name was</hi> Job, <hi>and he was a ſimple and an upright Man;</hi> as excelling in that above other Vertues. This our Lord commanded, when he ſent his Apoſtles into the whole World, to gather Unbelievers to the Unity of the Catholick Faith; ſaying, <hi>Math.</hi> 10. <hi>Be ye prudent as Serpents, and ſimple as Doves.</hi> Where Prudence is joyned to Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity: for Prudence without Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity is Craft; and Simplicity without Prudence, is Folly. The Dove neither hurts with her Beak, nor with her Talons; ſo the truly ſimple hurts neither with word nor Deed.</p>
               <p>He truly loves Simplicity, who is not buſied about many things; as <hi>Martha</hi> was, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. For, where there are many things, there are
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:38619:90"/>Doubles or Folds. But only ſeeks one thing; of which, our Lord; <hi>but one thing is neceſſary,</hi> for which <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> is commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>Who choſe the beſt part which ſhall not be taken away from her.</hi> This is that one Good, in which are all Goods eternal and immenſe.</p>
               <p>The Profit coming from Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity ought to induce us therunto. For it is written <hi>Pro.</hi> 3. <hi>And with the Simple is his Converſe;</hi> that is, the Lords. For the Lord is fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar with the ſimple, to whom he does not diſdain to reveal his Secrets. Whence our Lord, <hi>Math.</hi> 10. ſaid to his Apoſtles, prohibiting lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Children to come into his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, <hi>Permit little Children, and do not hinder them from coming to me, for of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> This is a Virtue without which there is no Salvation: For our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſays, <hi>Math.</hi> 18. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs ye be made
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:38619:90"/>like little Childeren, ye ſhall not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> He does not ſay, unleſs ye be made little Children, but like little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; that is Simple and Innocent. Another Profit of Simplcity is, that which is mentioned, <hi>Pro.</hi> 10. <hi>He who walks ſimply walks confidently.</hi> For the way of Simplicity is the moſt ſecure way to the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. For it is written, <hi>He will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect thoſe who walk ſimply, Pro.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, who perverts no bodies doings, but preſumes well of all; who neither depraves, nor dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes any ones Good; who deſires the Salvation of all, and wiſhes ill to none: who does good things, and does them well; <hi>And who has good thoughts of the Lord, and ſeeks him in the ſimplicity of his heart, Wiſdom.</hi> 1. Who ſubmits himſelf to his will, and keeps his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:38619:91"/>
               <p>He has an Argument of Dupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, who has one thing in his Mouth, and another in his Heart and works; As <hi>Joab</hi> holding <hi>Amaza</hi> by the Chin, ſaid, <hi>Brother, God ſave you;</hi> and in the mean time ſecretly drawing out a Sword, ſlew him, 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 20. Againſt this our Lord Jeſus ſays, <hi>Let your Speech be Yea, yea, Nay, Nay, Math.</hi> 5. That is, what you have in your Heart, ſpeak with your Mouth, and exhibit with your Deeds. And S. <hi>James, Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>The double minded man is inconſtant in all his ways.</hi> And God curſes double Dealers; to wit, who will together ſerve him and the Devil; that is, exerciſe themſelves in Sins, and in good Works. For theſe our Lord ſays, <hi>Math.</hi> 6. <hi>No body can ſerve two, Maſters;</hi> to wit, that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to one another. For Vertue and Vice, Good and Evil, are whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite. Againſt thoſe who ſeek
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:38619:91"/>to pleaſe God and the World, S. <hi>James</hi> ſayes, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>Whoſoever will be a friend of this World is made an enemy of God</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has an Argument of falſe Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, who makes a ſhew of Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity in his outward Converſation, and yet carries Deceit in his Heart; Of ſuch an one the Prophet <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> ſays, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. <hi>Let every one keep himſelf from his Neighbour, and let him not have confidence in every Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; becauſe every Brother, ſupplant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, will ſupplant, and every Friend will walk deceitfully.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXI. <hi>Of Silence.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE and perfect Silence is, not only to reſtrain the Tongue from unlawfull Words (as are Detractions, Lyes, Perjuries, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſte,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:38619:92"/>light, angry, hurtful, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful Words, and ſuch like; but alſo from profitable and lawfull; according to that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. <hi>I held my Peace, and was humbled; I was ſilent from good things:</hi> that is, from declaiming them. The Gloſſ. ſays, He does no fall into unlawfull things who warily raſtrains himſelf from thoſe that are lawfull. Spiritual Grace is poured out not only by unprofitable and hurtfull Words but by profitable Words, when a mean is not obſerved in ſpeaking. This moderation of the Tongue is a rare Virtue: Witneſs S. <hi>James Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>All Beaſts, and Fowls, and Serpents, and other living Creatures, are tamed, and have been tamed by man; but the Tongue no man can tame; it is a reſtleſs Evil; full of dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Poyſon.</hi> The Gloſs: the Tongue of wicked men, ſurpaſſes the Beaſts in Cruelty, the Birds in Levity, the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:38619:92"/>Serpents in Virulency: For they are Beaſts <hi>who have ſharpened their Tongues like a ſword,</hi> Pſal. 63. They are Birds who have put their mouth in Heaven, and <hi>whoſe Mouth has ſpoken Vanity, Pſal.</hi> 143. They are Serpents, of whom it is ſaid; <hi>The Poyſon of Aſps is under their Lips, Pſal.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>The moſt holy example of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ought to induce us to the love of Silence; who, ſo recommended Silence, when he was asked concerning Crimes falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laid to his Charge, would not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe himſelf nor by any Anſwer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his death. The example alſo of a certain <hi>Eremite,</hi> ought to move us hereunto; concerning whom we read that he carried a Stone in his Mouth three years that he might learn to keep Silence; for one may ſooner learn to ſpeak, than to be Silent, according to that of a Wiſe
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:38619:93"/>man; <hi>He who knows how to ſpeak, let him learn alſo to hold his peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Profit coming from it, ought to induce us to it. For Silence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the diſtracted Heart, induces quiet of Conſcience: and makes the mind apt to receive the Divine Grace. But where there is not Silence, there a man is eaſily overcome by the Adverſary: according to that <hi>Pro.</hi> 25. <hi>As an open City and without Walls: ſo is the man who cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain his Spirit in ſpeaking:</hi> For where there is not a moderation of the Tongue, there will never be Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; according to that, <hi>James</hi> 3. <hi>If any one offend not in his Words he is a perfect man.</hi> And no other, ſaies the Gloſs: Where there is a cuſtody of the Tongue, there is Happineſs; according to that, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Bleſſed is the man who has not faln by a word out of his Mouth.</hi> And <hi>Pro.</hi> 21. <hi>He who keeps his mouth
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:38619:93"/>and his Tongue, keeps his Soul from ſtraits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has an argument of true Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, who when he may freely, and lawfully, and without offence, ſpeak, and whoſe words would be received with great deſire, and yet can by no means or very rarely be induced to ſpeak, remembring that of <hi>S. Gregory;</hi> If the holy Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was ſent to ſpeak, and yet ſat ſilent and weeping ſeven days, we ought to conſider, how great a fault it is for him not to be ſilent, whom no neceſſity compels to ſpeak. And that Evangelical word, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. <hi>But I ſay unto you, that every idle word that men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall give an account thereof in the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe Silence or Loquacity is, to ſpeak malapert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and clamorouſly, that he may ſeem to be ſome body amongſt others;
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:38619:94"/>Or in an importune time, whereas ſeaſonable Speech is the beſt. Againſt this is that, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 20. <hi>A wiſe man will hold his peace until a fit time, but the wanton and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent will not obſerve time.</hi> Or to ſpeak when no body attends, or cares to hear: Againſt that is, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 32. <hi>Where there is no hearing do not poure forth Speech.</hi> Or when one anſwers before he hears, or be ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Againſt this, <hi>Pro.</hi> 18. <hi>He who anſwers before he hears, ſhows himſelf to be a Fool, and worthy of confuſion.</hi> Or when he anſwers for another, not being asked: Againſt that is, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 32. <hi>Young man, ſcarce ſpeak in thy own Cauſe: if thou ſhalt be asked twice, let thy anſwer have a head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe Silence is, not to be ſilent out of Virtue, but leſt he ſhould be confounded before the hearers. Or that he may be praiſed for his Silence. Or when
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:38619:94"/>he is aſhamed to ſpeak, knowing not how to ſpeak underſtandingly, or profitably. Or that his folly may be covered by his Silence, according to that, <hi>A Fool if he hold his peace, ſhall be acounted a wiſe man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXII. <hi>Of Solitude.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Solitude is, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract the Mind from the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitude and inordinate employ of exteriour Actions, from all delight of Creatures and unanimuoſly to direct, as much as we can, all our Affections, Wills and Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unto God, that we might be made one Spirit with him; to this the Prophet <hi>Eſaias</hi> exhorts us, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>ſaying: Enter into the Rock, and hide thy ſelf in the digged earth. Enter</hi> into the Rock, that is, into the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:38619:95"/>Divinity of Chriſt; hide thy ſelf in the digged Earth, that is, in the Wounds of Chriſt: he who is in this Rock is alone; he who is out of this Rock is in a Crowd of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. In this Solitude of Mind ſo great Grace and illumination of Mind is received, that the Receiver is offenſive to others to behold. As <hi>Moſes</hi> remaining alone with God in the Mountain, forty days and forty Nights, was ſo illuminated, that the Light broke forth into his Face, and from the ſhining of his Countenance, proceeded, as it were Rayes of the Sun, which the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were not able to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, until he covered his Face with a Veil, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.</p>
               <p>The moſt holy Example of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt ought to move us to the love of Solitude, who, though he could not by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of any be hindred from
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:38619:95"/>his Spiritual Employ, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, he often retired from Company for the love of Solitude: and ſometimes, when he could not go farther off, he withdrew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Stones caſt from his deareſt Apoſtles, that he might attend to Prayer; as St. <hi>Luke</hi> writes, <hi>ch.</hi> 22. Hereby inſinuating unto us, that even holy men, amidſt the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, cannot familiarly converſe with God, or do get little or no efficacious Grace amongſt Men. Hence it is, that <hi>Zacheus</hi> could not ſee our Lord Jeſus in the Crowd; but afterwards he ſaw him, and heard his Voice, when alone he climbed up into a Tree, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>The profit alſo of Solitude ought to induce us unto it; concerning which, our Lord ſays of his Spouſe, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2. <hi>I will lead her into the Wilderneſs, and ſpeak to her Heart.</hi> O how happy is he who even once
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:38619:96"/>once hears our Lord ſpeaking with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him: The ſpeaking of the Lord in the Heart, is to give Aſſurance of Mind concerning heard Graces. It ought to move us to the ſame, that holy <hi>Eremites</hi> of old ran into Deſarts, Mountains, Dens, and Caves of the Earth, that they might continually attend to God, and ſometimes ſaw not a Man for forty Years.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, who with pain is in the Company of Men; and takes all occaſions to withdraw himſelf from them. <hi>Behold I have fled a great way off, and have remained in Solitude, Pſal.</hi> 54. As it was a Pain to S. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Magdalen</hi> to ſee Men, after ſhe could no longer ſee her Lord <hi>Jeſus;</hi> yea it was painful to her even to ſee Angels: whence, when the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels went about to comfort her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Departure of our Lord
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:38619:96"/>out of his Sepulcher, ſhe ſays, I ſeek the Creator, and therefore it is grievous to me to ſee the Creature. And therefore ſhe fled into the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, for the love of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, thirty years, wanting all corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Meat and Drink, whom the Angels elevated into the Air at her ſet hours of Prayer; in which Prayer, ſhe received the Nutriment of Soul and Body.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of falſe So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, who though he be alone with God corporally, yet his Soul is occupied in variety of Buſineſſes, in diverſe parts of the World. Theſe two things, Silence and Solitude, do efficaciouſly elevate to Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation: Whence that of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations,</hi> chap. 3. <hi>He ſhall ſit alone and be ſilent, becauſe he has elevated himſelf above himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:38619:97"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXIII. <hi>Of Contemplation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TRUE and perfect Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation is, a Collection of all the Affections and Forces of the Soul, to know with delight and admiration of Mind, ſomething of the Divine Nature; to wit, of the Divine Power, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, Charity, Excellency, Liberality,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or to know the ſecret Judgments of God, or his moſt holy Will, or ſome Perfection which tends unto him. This Contemplation had the Holy Patriarchs, Prophets, and Apoſtles: for, God revealed his Secrets by his holy Spirit to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs and Prophets. To</hi> Noah <hi>he revealed the Flood,</hi> Gen. <hi>7. To</hi> Abraham <hi>the Deſtruction of the</hi> Sodomites, Gen. <hi>18. To</hi> Jeremy <hi>the
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:38619:97"/>Tranſmigration and Captivity of the</hi> Jews. <hi>To</hi> Joſeph <hi>the Famine in</hi> Aegypt, Gen. <hi>47. To</hi> Daniel <hi>the Tree of</hi> Nebuchodonozor, Dan. <hi>4. The like of other Patriarchs and Prophets, to whom God revealed his Secrets; as diverſe Viſions to</hi> Ezekiel, chap. <hi>1. whence</hi> Amos, <hi>ch. 3.</hi> The Lord God will not do a Word, unleſs he reveal his ſecret to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. <hi>But he revealed all his Will and all Perfection to his Apoſtles by his only begotten Son; as he ſays,</hi> Jo. <hi>15.</hi> All things whatſoever which I have heard of my Father, I have made known unto you. <hi>To the end, that they might reveal the ſame to Poſterity; which alſo they have faithfully done.</hi> For their ſound went out into all the Earth, and their Words unto the ends of the World, Pſal. <hi>18. But amongſt the Apoſtles, he revealed and declared his greateſt Secrets to S.</hi> John <hi>the
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:38619:98"/>Evangeliſt, and to S.</hi> Paul. <hi>Amongſt other things, he revealed to them the eight Beatitudes; ſaying,</hi> Mat. <hi>5.</hi> Bleſſed are the poor in Spirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Bleſſed are the Meek, <hi>&amp;c. which Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitudes, contain in them great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and declare the perfect Will of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is a difference betwixt Contemplation, Meditation, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation: for, in Cogitation the Mind wanders; in Meditation it finds out ſomething; in Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation it admires. Cogitation is without Labour and without Fruit; Meditation is with Labour and with Fruit; Contemplation is without Labour, and with Fruit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We are brought to the Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of God by three Degrees: concerning which, St.</hi> Gregory, The firſt is, That the Soul recollect it ſelf to it ſelf. The Second is, that it ſee it ſelf, what it is, thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collected.
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:38619:98"/>The Third is, That it ariſe above it ſelf, and ſubmit it ſelf, attending to the Contemplation of it's inviſible Maker. But it can by no means recollect it ſelf to it ſelf, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it have firſt learnt to reſtrain the Phantaſms of terreſtrial and celeſtial Images from the Eye of the Mind; unleſs it have learnt to reject and trample upon whatſoever ſhall occur to it's Thought from the corporeal Sight, Hearing, Smelling, Taſting or Touching, that it may ſeek it ſelf ſuch within, as it is without thoſe: for, whilſt it thinks upon thoſe things it turns over within it ſelf as it were certain ſhadows of Bodies. Therefore all thoſe things are to be driven away from the Eyes of the Mind, by the hand of Diſcretion, that the Soul may conſider it ſelf ſuch, as it is created under God above the Body; that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vivificated by the Superior, it may vivificated the Inferior, which it adminiſters.</p>
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:38619:99"/>
               <p>We often will conſider the inviſible nature of Almighty God, but we are not able; and the Soul wearied with thoſe difficulties, returns to it ſelf, and makes to it ſelf, of it ſelf, degrees of Aſcenſions; that firſt of all if it be able, it may conſider it ſelf, and then find out that Nature which is above it, as far as it is able. But, if our Mind ſhall be diſperſed in carnal Images, it is by no means ſufficient to conſider it ſelf, or the Nature of the Soul: becauſe by as many Thoughts as it is lead, it is as it were, blinded by ſo many Obſtacles. The firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree therefore is, that the Soul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Motives to Contemplation are, the ineffable Sweetneſs which is there perceived; the admirable Perfection which is there learn'd; the principal of all Beatitude which is there found: for the Fountain of all Beatitude, the moſt High God, is there known; and what is
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:38619:99"/>known, that is loved; and what is truly loved, is deſired and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured for, that it may be obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and what is induſtriouſly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured for, that is at length acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and when at length it ſhall be acquired, it is poſſeſſed with endleſs Delight. Of this St.</hi> Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard; A Soul which has once learnt of our Lord, and has received of him to enter into her ſelf, and in her moſt inward receſſes to pant after the preſence of God, and to ſeek his Face alwayes; (for God is a Spirit, and they who ſeek him muſt walk in the Spirit, and not in the Fleſh, that they may live according to the Fleſh) Such a Soul, I ſay, I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe would count it more horrible and painful to experiment Hell it ſelf for a time, than after having taſted the Sweetneſs of this ſpiritual Study, to go out again to the Allurements, or rather to the Troubles of the Fleſh,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:38619:100"/>and to return to the inſatiable Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the Senſes; <hi>Eccleſiaſtes ſaying,</hi> chap. <hi>2.</hi> The Eye is not ſatisfied with ſeeing, nor the Ear with hearing. <hi>For, hear an experienced man what he ſays,</hi> Thou art good, ſays he, <hi>O</hi> Lord, to thoſe who hope in thee, to the Soul which ſeeks thee. From this Good, if any one ſhould have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to have averted that holy Soul, I believe he would hardly have taken it otherwiſe than if he ſhould have ſeen himſelf to have been caſt out of Paradiſe, and from the very Entrance of Glory. Hear yet another like unto this: My Heart, ſays he, has ſaid to thee, my Face has ſought thee, thy Face, <hi>O</hi> Lord, will I ſeek. Whence he ſaid, But it is good for me to adhere to God. And alſo ſpeaking to his Soul, he ſays, Be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, <hi>O</hi> my Soul, into thy Reſt, becauſe the Lord has done well unto thee. I ſay therefore unto you, that
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:38619:100"/>there is nothing which one who has received this Favour does ſo much fear, as leſt being left by the Divine Grace, it ſhould be neceſſary for him to go out again to the Conſolations, yea the Deſolations, of the Fleſh, and again to ſuffer the Tumults of his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Senſes. <hi>In this Contemplation was St.</hi> Auguſtin, <hi>when he ſaid,</hi> But it diſpleaſed me, that I lived in the World, and it was a great burden to me, my ſenſual Deſires not now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flaming me as they were wont, with the hope of Honour and Money, to endure that ſo grievous Servitude. For now thoſe things did not delight me, by reaſon of thy ſweetneſs, and of the beauty of thy Houſe, which I lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He has an Argument of true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation who is weary of living in this miſerable World; ſaying with B.</hi> Tobias, <hi>chap. 3.</hi> It is better for me to dye than to live. <hi>And with
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:38619:101"/>H.</hi> Job, <hi>chap. 10.</hi> My Soul is weary of my Life. <hi>And with St.</hi> Paul, Rom. <hi>7.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy Man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from the Body of this Death? <hi>And he who thirſts after the Fountain of Life, ſaying with the Pſalmiſt,</hi> As the Hart thirſts after Fountains of Water, ſo thirſts my Soul after thee, <hi>O</hi> God, <hi>Pſal. 41. Whence St.</hi> Gregory, A contemplative Life is, to retain indeed in the heart the Love of God and our Neighbour; but to reſt from exterior Action, and to inhere only in the deſire of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, ſo that nothing is now to be done: but all Cares being trampled under Foot, the Soul burns with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee the Face of it's Creator: ſo that now it knows how to bear with Grief the weight of the corruptible Fleſh, and with all it's Forces to deſire to be preſent amidſt the ſweet-ſinging Quires of Angels, and to be mixed with the caeleſtial Citizens, to
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:38619:101"/>rejoyce before God for eternal Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He has an Argument of falſe Contemplation, who holds ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning God, or ſome Perfection of God, contrary to the Holy Scriptures, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he temerariouſly defends by Reaſons. And hence came He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies of old, to wit, that of</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, <hi>who denied the Son to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eternal and conſubſtantial with the Father: And that of</hi> Sabellius, <hi>who confounded the Perſons in the Trinity, putting only a nominal difference, whereas they truly dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in their Properties. For the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther properly has Innaſcibility, the Son properly Naſcibility, the Holy Ghoſt Proceſſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:38619:102"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXIV. <hi>Of Diſcretion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Diſcretion is, prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to judge betwixt the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and the Creature: what the Creator is, and what the Creature. Alſo to diſcern what is good, what better, and what the beſt of all: what is bad, what worſe, &amp; what the worſt of all: How much God is to be deſired, and how much Evil to be deteſted: Alſo what Reverence one ought to have to his Superior, what Clemency and Compaſſion to his Inferior, and what Society to his Equal: how he ought to behave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Dead, how to the Living: how to his Predeceſſors, and how to thoſe that are to ſucceed him: How to his Friends, that they be loved in God: and how to his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:38619:102"/>that they be loved for God: How ſecretly before God, and how openly before men: What refection is to be given to the Fleſh, and what to the Spirit: What Cloths he is to wear: When he is to eat, when to drink, when to abſtain, and how much, and from what meats: when to Watch, and when to ſleep, and how much and how long: When to pray, when to weep, and when to do any work: How to behave himſelf to praiſe, and how to reprove: When to ſpeak, and when to be ſilent: how much, for what cauſes, with whom, in what place and at what time: When to receive, when to retain, and when to give, and how much, and to whom, and and at what time: To order, and prudently to diſcern. Concerning all theſe things, is the work of true Diſcretion. This Vertue is the miſtreſs of all Virtues, appointing unto them
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:38619:103"/>all their Meaſure and Order. But where diſcretion is not, there charity does not obſerve Order: What is to be loved in the firſt place, and what in the laſt: nor meaſure what is to be loved leſs, and what more.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> teſtifies, where Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility is too much obſerved the Autority of him that rules is broken; There obedience is blind and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh where one believes he is to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, even in ill things. There Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality is too profuſe, when one gives without Neceſſity to Stage-players. Where Diſcretion is not, there Fear is dejected into Deſpair, and Hope is turned into Preſumti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. There Juſtice ſhews too great Severity. There Patience, Mercy, Meekneſs, Benignity, Goodneſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble unjuſt things. There Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is diſſolved into Licentiouſnes, Truth falſified, Chaſtity violated,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:38619:103"/>Maturity made light, Conſtancy quite changed.</p>
               <p>This Virtue encreaſes by the fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of other Virtues: For, when a man often falls from Humility into Pride, or Vain-glory, from Charity into Envy, from Patience into Anger, from Meekneſs into Rancor, from Fervor into Tepidity, from Chaſtity into carnal Concupiſcence, from love of Poverty into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, from Peace into Diſquiet, from Union into Diſcord, from Obedience into Rebellion, from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutiry into Levity, from Religion into Diſſolution, from Silence into Talkativeneſs or Detraction, from ſpiritual Love into Carnal, from Hope, into Preſumption, from a juſt Fear into Humane and Servile, from Juſtice into Severity, from Mercy into Softneſs, from Conſtancy into Mutableneſs, from Truth into Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; then indeed one is made
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:38619:104"/>more cautious, and more ſollicitous and diſcreet in all things.</p>
               <p>Helps to true Diſcretion are, diligent reading and meditation in the Holy Scriptures, continual ſearch into the Examples of Saints, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Counſel from diſcreet Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; according to that, <hi>Tob.</hi> 4. <hi>Alwayes ask counſel of the wiſe.</hi> Whence our Lord to <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 9. <hi>Ariſe, and enter into the City, and it ſhall be told thee what thou art to do.</hi> In like manner he ſent the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, <hi>Luke</hi> 17. <hi>Go ſhew your ſelves to the Prieſts.</hi> Not to one only, but to more; that if one be leſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet, another more diſcreet may be ſought.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, who does all his works with the counſel of the Diſcreet; whom, if he cannot always have, he diſcuſſes all his Works and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in his own Conſcience before
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:38619:104"/>God, with true Diſcretion and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Deliberation; according to that, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 32. <hi>Son, do nothing without counſel, and thou ſhalt not repent thee afterwards.</hi> Yet let him not in this neither always believe his own Conſcience, unleſs he have the manifeſt teſtimony of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. Neither let him by any means wreſt the Scripture to his own ſenſe, but conform his ſenſe to the Scripture.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, who above his ſtrength la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, in Watchings, Faſtings, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Diſciplines, and Tears, deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf in a ſhort time: he is made unprofitable in the Service of God for many years. But alas! there are few in our days guilty of this Exceſs.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of falſe Diſcretion, who, being careful not to deſtroy his Body, neglects no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:38619:105"/>which makes for its commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, ſaying to the Lord, <hi>My Strength I will keep for thee. Pſal.</hi> 58. And in the mean time, the Spirit faints and pines away for want of ſpiritual Food, which by no means can be had without Labour: whence St. <hi>Auguſtin, Whilſt we fear the weakneſs of our Fleſh, we neglect the health of our Soul.</hi> Becauſe the Fleſh, if it be daintily fed, kills the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>As the Moth eats up the Wool, and the Fire conſumes Wood, Hey, and Straw, ſo the rebellious and dainty Fleſh burns up, and conſumes the Soul.</hi> Such an one does not conſider, that at length his Fleſh ſhall be deſtroyed, although it ſhould enjoy all ſorts of Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. As Secular People, giving all pleaſure to their Bodies, do not ſerve God the more, but are more frequently ſick. However, it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the Spirit ſhould live, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:38619:105"/>with Grace, in a languid Body, than that it ſhould be lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guid or dead in a ſound Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXV. <hi>Of Congratulation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Congratulation which regards God, is to rejoyce with God for all his Beatitude and eternal, innate Perfection; to wit, for his Omnipotency, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that he wants nothing, but is ſufficient for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and all Creatures.</p>
               <p>Alſo to rejoyce with God for the orderly Diſpoſition of Heaven and Earth, and of all things that are in them; and for all his Works from the beginning of the World to the end thereof: eſpecially for the works of his Incarnation, Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, Paſſion, Reſurrection, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:38619:106"/>and Miſſion of the Holy Ghoſt; and for all his Judgments, manifeſt and ſecret, about Devils, about Souls in Hell, <hi>Lymbus,</hi> and <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and about wicked men in the World. Alſo, to rejoyce with God for whatſoever Praiſe and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he has, from Angels and Saints in Heaven, and from Men on Earth.</p>
               <p>True Congratulation to our Neighbours is, to rejoyce with all the Angels and Saints, for their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Heaven: to rejoyce with the B. Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> with the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs and Prophets, with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and all the Elect, with all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men in the Church and upon Earth, for all the gifts they have received, and ſhall receive from God. Alſo, to rejoyce with Sinners for their Converſion; with the Juſt for their Confortation and Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in Grace, and with the
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:38619:106"/>Church for the Sacraments and Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>The exceeding great profit of true Congratulation, ought to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us thereunto; for, whatſoever Perfection, Goodneſs, and Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, the omnipotent God has na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally in himſelf; whatſoever Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Angels and Saints have in Heaven, and whatſoever Grace and Virtue there is in the Church, and the faithful have in it, all this, by Congratulation, is made proper to every one. It ought to induce us to the ſame alſo, that the Congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, is the Origine of all Creatures; and always was, and now is, the Principle of all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Works.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Congratulation, who is delighted in all things which are in God; whom the Order of the Church,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:38619:107"/>and all die Works and Judgments of God, and the Divine Manners, and moſt holy Examples of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and of all his Friends, do heartily pleaſe; and he commends them all with his Words, and manifeſts them to others. Alſo, who has ſpiritual Joy in all the natural, ſpiritual, and gratuit Gifts of the Angels and Saints in Heaven, and of all men on Earth, and always, and every where according to his Power, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operates with them all.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of falſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulation, who with his Mouth commends all the Divine Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Heaven and in Earth, and the Works of the Juſt and their Virtues, and their holy Life, but diſpraiſes them all in his Heart: ſuch our Lord upbraids in <hi>Eſaias, chap.</hi> 29. <hi>This People draws near to me with their Mouth, and honours
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:38619:107"/>me with their Lips, but their Heart is far from me.</hi> Such are cut off from the Body of the Church, who do not by Congratulation, partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the Goods of the Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXVI. <hi>Of Confidence.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TRUE and perfect Confidence is a Security of Mind, that the omnipotent and faithful God never leaves his Friends; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that,</hi> Eccleſ. <hi>2.</hi> No body has hoped in God, and was confounded. for, who has remained in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and was forſaken?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He has true Confidence who is aſſured, that the good God is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways preſent with his Servants in their Afflictions, and is always rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to deliver them out of Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to glorifie whom he has
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:38619:108"/>delivered: according to that,</hi> Pſal. <hi>90.</hi> I am with him in Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I will deliver him, and will glorifie him. <hi>As he was with</hi> Daniel <hi>in the Lyons Den,</hi> Dan. <hi>14. With</hi> Noah <hi>in the Ark,</hi> Gen. <hi>7. With</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph <hi>in the Ciſtern,</hi> Gen. <hi>37. With the three Children in the fiery Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace,</hi> Dan. <hi>3. And all theſe he moſt graciouſly delivered. Whence S.</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>2 Epiſt. 2.</hi> The Lord knows how to deliver the Godly out of Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>And</hi> Sarah <hi>ſays in</hi> Tobias, <hi>ch. 3.</hi> This every one who worſhips thee holds for certain, that his Life if it ſhall have been proved, it ſhall be crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but, and if he ſhall have been in Tribulation, he ſhall be delivered; and if he ſhall have been in Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he may come to thy Mercy: For, thou art not delighted in our Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; becauſe after a Tempeſt thou makeſt a Calm, and after Tears and Weeping thou infuſeſt Joy.</p>
               <pb n="205" facs="tcp:38619:108"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>He has true Confidence who does not doubt, but that all his Prayers and all his juſt Deſires are heard. For, St.</hi> Chryſoſtom <hi>ſays,</hi> If thou ſhalt approach to God with this Zeal of Mind, and ſhalt ſay, I will not depart, (to wit, unleſs I receive) thou ſhalt certainly receive; if thou ask ſuch things as it behoves him to give who is asked, and as are expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for thee to receive who askeſt them. <hi>This Vertue is very lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and of great merit before God; to which the Apoſtle exhorts us, ſaying,</hi> Heb. <hi>10.</hi> Do not loſe your Confidence, which has a great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It ought to induce us to true Confidence, that the moſt liberal God, without our asking, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times gives us greater things, of his mere incomprehenſible Bounty, than we ſhould dare to ask: for, the Father has created us to the
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:38619:109"/>Image of the Trinity, and his moſt holy Son has given us his Fleſh for Food, and his Blood for Drink, and his Soul to be the price of our Redemption. And who could ever once have dared to think of ſuch gifts as theſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Poſture of our Lord Jeſus on his Croſs ought to induce us to the ſame: for of this St.</hi> Bernard <hi>ſays,</hi> Who would not be raiſed up to Hope, and to a Confidence of obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if he would conſider the poſture of the Body of Christ on the Croſs? Behold his Head bowed down to kiſs thee; his Arms ſtretched out to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thee; his Hands bored through to give thee Gifts; his Side opened to love thee; his whole Body ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth to beſtow his whole ſelf upon thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He has an Argument of true Confidence, whoſe Conſcience does not reprehend him of mortal Sins:
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:38619:109"/>witneſs St.</hi> John, <hi>1</hi>Epiſt. <hi>3.</hi> If our Heart reprehend us not, we have Confidence in God; and whatſoever we ask we ſhall receive from him. <hi>Whence we read of</hi> Suſanna, Dan. <hi>13.</hi> Her Heart had confidence in God, <hi>becauſe ſhe knew her ſelf innocent of the crime objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her. Another Argument of true Confidence he has, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually exerciſes himſelf in good Works, eſpecially in ſpiritual Alms, which is to remit Injuries; and moreover, to pray for thoſe who injure us: concerning which, it is ſaid in</hi> Tobias, chap. <hi>4.</hi> Almſgivings delivers from all Sin and from Death, and will not ſuffer the Soul to go into Darkneſs. Almſ-deeds are great Confidence before the moſt high God, to all that do them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another Argument of true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of the pardon of his Sins, he has, who does true Penance
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:38619:110"/>for them in his Youth and Health: witneſs St.</hi> Auguſtin; If any man in his last Sickneſs deſire to receive Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and does receive it, and is reconciled at the ſame time, and dies immediately, I confeſs unto you, that we do not indeed refuſe him what he demands; but alſo we do not preſume that he dies well: I do not preſume that, I will not deceive you, I do not preſume it. He who lives well after his Baptiſm, he who is baptized in the Article of Death, he who during his Health does Penance, is recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, and lives well afterwards; all theſe dye with Aſſurance of their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. But, as for him who does not Penance, and who is not reconciled, but upon his Death-bed; if you ask me if he dye with Aſſurance of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, I will anſwer you, that I am not aſſured of it. <hi>And a little after,</hi> Do I ſay then he ſhall be damned? I do not ſay ſo. But do I ſay then he
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:38619:110"/>ſhall be ſaved? No. What do I ſay then? I know not. I do not preſume, I do not promiſe, I know not. Would'ſt thou fee thy ſelf of this Doubt? Would'ſt thou avoid this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty? Do Penance whilſt thou art in Health; for, if thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt true Penance whilſt thou art in Health, and thy laſt Day ſhall come, run to be reconciled: if thou doeſt ſo thou art ſecure. Why art thou ſecure? Becauſe thou hast done Penance at that time when thou couldeſt alſo have ſinned. But if thou wilt then do Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance when thou canſt no longer ſin, thy Sins have left thee, not thou them. But thou ſayeſt, how do I know, if perhaps God may not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thee? Thou ſayeſt very true. How do I know? I know not. That I know, this I know not. For there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I give thee Penance, becauſe I know not. For, if I knew that it would profit thee nothing, I would
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:38619:111"/>not give it thee. Alſo, if I knew that it would profit thee, I would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh thee, I would not fright thee. There are two things; either thou ſhalt be pardoned, or thou ſhalt not he pardoned; which of theſe two ſhall be thy Lot, I know not: therefore lay hold on the certain, and let go the uncertain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They who deſire to obtain true Confidence, it behoves them to convert their Strength to ſpiritual Works; according to that of</hi> Eſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, chap. <hi>40.</hi> They who hope in the Lord ſhall change their Strength, they ſhall take Wings as an Eagle: they ſhall run, and not labour, they ſhall walk and not faint. <hi>That they who were before ſtrong to corporeal Labours, may afterwards be ſtrong to ſpiritual Labours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He has an Argument of Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, who not eſteeming the grace of Redemption, knowingly
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:38619:111"/>goes on in his Sins: whence in the Goſpel,</hi> Jo. <hi>9.</hi> We know, that God does not hear Sinners; but if any one be a Worſhipper of God, and do his Will, him he hears. <hi>And Pſal 65.</hi> If I have regarded Iniquity in my Heart, the Lord will not hear me. <hi>And</hi> Eſaias <hi>59.</hi> Your Iniquities have divided betwixt you and your God; and your Sins have hid his Face from you, that he ſhould not hear you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He has an Argument of falſe Confidence, who thinks the moſt juſt God will be ſo far overcome by Mercy and Pity, that in the day of Judgment he will ſave all, both good and bad, becauſe he has died for all: againſt this our Lord ſays,</hi> Matth. <hi>25.</hi> Theſe ſhall go into eternal Puniſhment, but the Juſt into eternal Life. <hi>He alſo has an Argument of falſe Confidence, who thinks a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner can deſerve the firſt Grace when
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:38619:112"/>he pleaſes. Alſo, if any one believe that he who abounds here in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Goods, ſhall abound hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in everlaſting Joy; againſt this it is ſaid,</hi> The Juſt ſhall ſee <hi>(to wit, the wicked Man in Hell)</hi> and ſhall fear, and ſhall laugh over him, and ſhall ſay, Behold the Man, who made not God his Helper; but hoped in the Multitude of his Riches, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed in his Vanity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXVII. <hi>Of the Contempt of the World.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A True Contempt of the World is, to renounce the temporal things of this Life, the Pomps of the World, all Dignities and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periorities, Spiritual and Secular, and to withdraw ones ſelf from all his carnal Friends, and ſecular Manners, for the hope of eternal
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:38619:112"/>Happineſs. To this S. <hi>John exhorts us,</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſtle</hi> 2. <hi>Do not love the World, nor thoſe things that are in the World.</hi> This Contempt S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> had, when whatſoever was done in the World diſpleaſed him: And when he diſcourſed with his Mother very ſweetly, and amidſt that Diſcourſe, the World with all its Delights was vile and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtful unto him. In like manner St. <hi>Agnes,</hi> St. <hi>Catharine,</hi> St. <hi>Cecily,</hi> and other Virgins, contemned the World, and all its Glory, for the love of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Worlds great unfaithfulneſs to it's Lovers at laſt ought to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us to the Contempt, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of it: For this was done even to the Creator himſelf by the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Worldlings; whom, upon <hi>Palm-ſunday</hi> they gloriouſly received, going out to meet him, and ſinging; <hi>Math.</hi> 21. <hi>Hoſanna to the Son of
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:38619:113"/>David; bleſſed is he who cometh in the name of the Lord, Hoſanna in the higheſt.</hi> But afterwards, on <hi>Good-Friday,</hi> they went forth crying to <hi>Pilate, Crucifie him, Crucifie him; if he had not been a Malefactor, we had not delivered him unto thee, Jo.</hi> 18. And when he hung upon the Croſs, they mocked him ſaying, <hi>ſave thy ſelf, if thou art the Son of God, Math.</hi> 27. And him whom they received with Palmes, Flowers, and green leaves, they crowned with pricking thorns, and beat with Rods and Whips; and for him whom they ſtrowed their own garments in the way, him they ſtript and ſpoiled of all his garments before the Croſs; and changed the Glory they gave him into Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.</p>
               <p>The danger which comes from the love of the World ought to induce us to the Contempt and
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:38619:113"/>Hatred of it; For St. <hi>James</hi> teſtifies, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>Know ye not, that the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of this World is Enmity with God; Whoſoever therefore will be a friend of this World, becomes an Enemy of God.</hi> And becauſe the World hated our Lord Jeſus, and all his Friends, as he told his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles for their Comfort, <hi>Jo.</hi> 15. <hi>If the World hate you, know that it hated me before it hated you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has an Argument of Contempt of the World, who cares not for Nobility of Parentage, nor ſeeks the Pleaſures of the Fleſh, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires Riches nor Honours. Such was <hi>Moſes,</hi> concerning whom the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>By Faith</hi> Moſes <hi>denied himſelf to be the Son of</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh's <hi>Daughter,</hi> (againſt Nobility) <hi>chuſing rather to be afflicted with the People of God, than to enjoy the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of Sin for a time,</hi> (againſt Pleaſure) <hi>eſteeming the Reproach of
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:38619:114"/>Chriſt, greater Riches than all the Treaſures of</hi> Egypt, (againſt Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es) <hi>for he had an Eye to the Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of Reward.</hi> He has another Argument of true Contempt of the World who is neither effeminared with the flatteries of the World, nor terrified with its Threats; nor is moved either with the Praiſe or Diſpraiſe of men. In this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the World was the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle; when he ſaid, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>I havè made all things as loſs, and I eſtèem them as Dung, that I may gain Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has an Argument of falſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the World who then firſt abſtains from the love of it, and its Allurements, when by reaſon of old Age and Poverty, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enjoy it. For then he does not leave the World, but is left by the World. As alas! how many are there, who then begin to leave off to ſin, when they can ſin no longer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <pb n="217" facs="tcp:38619:114"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXVIII. <hi>Of Mortification.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Mortification of the Fleſh is, when one volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily chaſtizes his Body with Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Watchings, Prayers, Hair-ſhirts, Diſciplines, and Abſtinence from delightful Meat and Drink, that in all things the Fleſh may be ſubject to the Spirit. This the Apoſtle did, when he ſaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>I chaſtize my Body, and bring it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſervitude, leſt perhaps when I ſhall have preached to others, I my ſelf may be a Reprobate.</hi> And <hi>Judith,</hi> who was fair and young, a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and rich, after ſhe had dwelt with her husband three years and ſix Months, from her Virginity ſhe had a Hair-ſhirt upon her
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:38619:115"/>loyns, and faſted every day, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Solemn Feaſts, <hi>Jud.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>The great Profit which comes from the mortification of the Fleſh ought to induce us to it. For by the mortification of the Fleſh the Spirit is ſtrengthened in Spiritual exerciſes. According to that of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>For when I am weak</hi> (in the Fleſh,) <hi>then I am ſtrong,</hi> (in Spirit.) And on the contrary, by the cheriſhing of the Fleſh, the rigor of the Spirit is damped in Spiritual exerciſes; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of St. <hi>Auguſtin, The delicate Fleſh burns up and conſumes the Soul as the Fire Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Argument of true Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is, when no Pleaſure, but only what's neceſſary, is allowed to the Fleſh: according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>We are Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, not to the Fleſh, that we ſhould
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:38619:115"/>live according to the Fleſh.</hi> For plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure exacts many more things, and more delicate, than neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; but neceſſity is contented with a few things. And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſubjoyns the Evil which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows Pleaſure, ſaying, <hi>If ye ſhall live according to the Fleſh, ye ſhall dye; but if by the Spirit ye ſhall mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Deeds of the Fleſh, ye ſhall live. But the Works of the Fleſh are manifeſt; which are, Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Immodeſty, Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Serving of Idols, Witchcrafts, Enmities, Contentions, Emulations, Angers, Brawlings, Diſſenſions, Sects, Envies, Murthers, Drunkenneſſes, Junkettings, and ſuch like: which I fore-tel you, as I have fore-told you, that they which do ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> Gal. 5.</p>
               <p>Another Argument is, when any one, according to the Counſel of
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:38619:116"/>Jeſus Chriſt, hates his own Soul in this World; for our Lord himſelf ſays, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. <hi>If any one come to me, and do not hate his Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Wife, and Children, and Brothers, and Siſters, and moreover his own Soul, he cannot be my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</hi> Which St. <hi>Gregory</hi> expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſays, <hi>For then we well hate our own Soul, when we do not yield to it's carnal Deſires; when we break it's Appetites, reſiſt it's Pleaſures: that therefore which by being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned is led to ſomething that's bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is, as it were, loved through Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</hi> But he who does not reſtrain his Soul from it's Concupiſcences, precipitates himſelf into the Snares of the Devil; according to that of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> chap. 18. <hi>If thou yieldeſt to thy Soul her Concupiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhe will make thee a Joy to thine Enemies.</hi> As <hi>Dalila</hi> delivered up the valiant <hi>Sampſon</hi> to the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins,</hi>
                  <pb n="221" facs="tcp:38619:116"/>to be mocked, <hi>Jud.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>He has not an Argument of true Mortification, who only bridles his Belly and Mouth from the Pleaſure of Meat and Drink, but bridles not his Tongue from unlawful Words, nor his Sight, Hearing, Taſting, Smell, and Touching, from their Delight, nor his Heart from volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Thoughts and Affections. For it is a ſmall matter, to reſtrain the Mouth and Belly from Meats, when the Heart and the five Senſes are ſed with Delights. Whence St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom, They who abſtain from Meats and do ill, they imitate the Devils, to whom not Meat but Wickedneſs is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways preſent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXIX. <hi>Of Contrition.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Contrition is a grief for Sins voluntarily aſſumed,
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:38619:117"/>according to the quantity and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Crimes, with a purpoſe of confeſſing and making Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, proceeding from the free grace of God: for, a natural Grief, or a Grief without grace, profits, or is good for nothing. <hi>Jeremy</hi> expreſſes the quantity of the Grief, when he ſays, Make to thy ſelf the mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for an only Son. This the Lord commanded in <hi>Joel,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Cut your Hearts.</hi> To this cutting are helpful the Thorns, Nails, Rods, Whips, Croſs and Spear, which cut the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. True Contrition is very rare, as teſtifies St. <hi>Gregory.</hi> We muſt know, that there are ſome, who although lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the World, they offer indeed all they have, and yet have not Compunction in the good things which they do: nor muſt we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways believe there is true Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction where there are Sighs and
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:38619:117"/>Tears; for, ſuch things are often wont to come from the fear of Hell, or from the conſideration of ſome Damage, or from natural Grief, or from natural Compaſſion, when one remembers the Enormity of his Crimes, or the moſt bitter Paſſion of Jeſus Chriſt. To true Contrition is required a grief for all the Sins we have committed, and for all the good we have omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and for all the Graces neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to our ſelves and others; and alſo, for thoſe which might, by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of us, be committed or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected.</p>
               <p>It will move us to true Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if we ſeriouſly think what we have loſt by Sin, to wit, the Holy Ghoſt with his Gifts, and all gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit Graces, the Friendſhip of the B. Trinity, and the Society of the celeſtial Court. Alſo, what we have got by Sin, to wit, eternal
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:38619:118"/>Death, the Malediction of God the Father; as the Pſalmiſt teſtifies, Pſal. 118. <hi>Curſed are they who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from thy Commandments.</hi> The Hatred of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt who hates all thoſe who work Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. The departure of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Who takes himſelf away</hi> even <hi>from Thoughts, which are without <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> as he ſays in the book of <hi>Wiſdom, chap.</hi> 1. But much more from wicked Works; for theſe are worſe, and more hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, than the very pains of Hell; as ſays St. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The great Profit alſo proceeding from the ſame, ought to induce us thereunto; for the leaſt Contrition, effaces all the blots of the Soul, kills eternal Death, confers the Benediction of God the Father, reſtores the Friendſhip of God the Son, the Familiarity of the Holy Ghoſt, and the Society of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernal
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:38619:118"/>Citizens: And Contrition how little ſoever it be, more ſatisfies than the greateſt Alms we can give. All theſe things, often weighed in the ballance of the Heart, are indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of true Compunction.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Contrition, who does ſo deteſt the filthineſs of Sin, that he would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chuſe all the pains of Purgatory, than commit any Sin againſt his moſt gracious God; and who would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf rather to the pains of Hell (with <hi>Eleazarus</hi>) than, for the future, deliberately commit any Sin: which alſo St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſays, ought rather to be choſen. And who would moſt willingly endure the torments of all the Martyrs, that he might hereby merit, never more to commit any Sin; and who would offer himſelf to all the Sufferings of the Sick and Poor, that he might duely ſatisfie God for his Offences.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of falſe
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:38619:119"/>Contrition, who, although he weep bitterly for the Sins he has committed, yet inſtantly after his Grief, he is not afraid to commit the ſame, or other Sins. Againſt this, it is ſaid in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> ch. 34. <hi>He who is waſhed from the Dead, and again touches the dead, what doth his waſhing profit him?</hi> In like manner, he who is ſorry for his paſt Sins, and does not reſolve, for the future, to leave his Sins, to wit, his Pride, Envy, carnal Friendſhip, fleſhly Delights, or the unjuſt Poſſeſſion of the Goods of others: Concerning which S <hi>Auguſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> ſays, <hi>The Sin is not forgiven, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les that which was taken away be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> Againſt this it is ſaid in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus, Chap.</hi> 34. <hi>One buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and another throwing down, what profit have they, but their Labour?</hi> He throws down, who is ſorry for his Sins: he builds who continues in a will to Sin: concerning ſuch a
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:38619:119"/>building St. <hi>Auguſtin ſays, Out of a perverſe will, is made luſt or deſire; And whilſt luſt is ſerved, there is made a cuſtom; And whilſt a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom is not reſiſted, there is made a neceſſity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XL. <hi>Of Confeſſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Confeſſion is a ſincere and rightful manifeſtation of Sins, without concealment, to a Prieſt. This our Lord commanded when he ſaid to the Lepers, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. <hi>Go ſhew your ſelves to the Priest.</hi> And St. <hi>James,</hi> chap. 5. <hi>Confeſs your Sins to one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To true Confeſſion it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that it be entire, pure, diſcreet, faithful, and perfect. According to that of <hi>Lamentations.</hi> 2. <hi>Pour out thy Heart as Water, before the ſight of the Lord. By pouring out</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Integrity; for we muſt
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:38619:120"/>not induſtriouſly tell our Sins by drops, which we have never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed: but whatſoever we can to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether call to Mind, muſt altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be poured out before one Prieſt, <hi>(as Water.)</hi> Where it is noted, Confeſſion ought to be ſimple and pure, not made out of ſervile Fear, or by Compulſion; but purely and ſimply for God. <hi>(Thy Heart.)</hi> where is noted Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. For not only our Words and Deeds, Commiſſions and Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, are to be confeſſed, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo our unclean Thoughts and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe Affections, inordinate Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, noxious Wills; perverſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and raſh Suſpicions: for, <hi>Origen</hi> ſays, That in that day, Thoughts ſhall accuſe and defend Souls: not the Thoughts which then ſhall be, but which are now in us, of which, certain Marks ſhall be left in the Heart, as it were in Wax. <hi>Before the Sight of God.</hi>
                  <pb n="229" facs="tcp:38619:120"/>Where is noted the Fidelity and Perfection of Confeſſion; for all things are to be conſidered accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Acknowledgment of God: for, where we acknowledge one Sin, he, in his Wiſdom, ſees a thouſand.</p>
               <p>The aſſured Remiſſion of Sins, and the cleanſing of the Soul, ought to induce us to a true Confeſſion: according to that, 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 1. <hi>If we confeſs our Sins, he is faithful and juſt to forgive us our Sins, and to cleanſe us from all Iniquity.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, are obliged to Remiſſion and Pardon, according to that: Although God knows all things, yet he expects the Voice of Confeſſion. For Chriſt has cauſe to intercede for thee, and the Father has cauſe to pardon thee, and whatſoever the Son wills, the Father alſo wills, and the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:38619:121"/>Confeſſion, who pours out all his Sins as Water, ſo that there remain neither colour, as in the pouring out of Milk; nor Fatneſs or Savor, as in the pouring out of Oyl or Blood; nor ſmell, as in the pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out of Wine or Vinegar. The colour remains when the Sin is told, but the Occaſion Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to ſin, is concealed; as it happens in Gluttony or Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Fatneſs or Savour remains when the Sin is told, but quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity or long continuance of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, in which Reaſon was wholly drowned, is concealed: according to that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 108. <hi>It has entred like Water into his Bowels, and like Oyl into his very Bones.</hi> The Smell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains when the Sin is told, but the Infamy or bad Example, and Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of others, is concealed. But, he who rightly confeſſes, manifeſts both the Sin, and what went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, and what followed after it.</p>
               <pb n="231" facs="tcp:38619:121"/>
               <p>It is an Argument of true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, when one confeſſes his Sins in Number, Weight, and Meaſure. We muſt confeſs in Number, that is, how often we have ſinned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Wound often renewed, is more ſlowly cured. Alſo in Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, when one confeſſes the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of Sin; for he who is lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſick ſooner dies. In Weight, that is, the grievouſneſs of our Sins: for Sin is aggravated from a ſacred Place, as a Church or Church-yard: from a ſacred Time or Perſon; as if it were a Clergy-man who was hurt, if a religious or married Perſon with whom one ſinned.</p>
               <p>An Argument of falſe Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, when one confeſſes leſt he ſhould be reputed an Infidel, or that he may be accounted more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or leſt the Holy Communion ſhould be denyed him, to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion: as <hi>Saul</hi> confeſſed, leſt he ſhould have been confounded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:38619:122"/>fore the People by the Prophet <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XLI. <hi>Of Penance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE external Penance is, an Abſtinence from lawful things when pardon is asked for unlawful; as ſays the Scripture. So Penitents and Religious Perſons ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from Fleſh, reject Fine Cloaths, Faſt, Watch, afflict themſelves with Diſciplines, keep Silence, break their own Will, and refrain from many Delights which would have been lawful to them, if they never had committed any thing unlawful. This our Lord, and S. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> commanded; ſaying, <hi>Do Penance, for the Kingdom of God is at hand, Math.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>The Neceſſity of true Penance ought to induce us thereunto; for without it there is no Salvation, our
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:38619:122"/>Lord ſaying, <hi>Luke</hi> 13. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs ye have Penance, ye ſhall all in like manner periſh.</hi> And S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> Sins, be they little, be they great, they cannot be unpuniſhed. Whence the Lord enjoyned <hi>David</hi> Penance for his Sin in numbring his People, that he ſhould either ſuffer ſeven years Famine, or three years the Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his Enemies, or three days Peſtilence: and <hi>David</hi> choſe for himſelf and his People the common ſcourge of Death. By this is ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that every one ſhall certainly be puniſhed for his Sins, either in Hell, ſignified by the ſeven years Famine, or in Purgatory, ſignified by the Violence of Enemies for three Months; or with temporal Puniſhment, ſignified by the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of three Years. So it is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to us to chooſe for our ſelves the eaſieſt Penance, and which ſoon paſſes away.</p>
               <pb n="234" facs="tcp:38619:123"/>
               <p>An Argument of true Penance is, a due commenſuration of the Pain to the Fault: that according to the quantity of the Fault, be the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity and gravity of the Pain: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the delight of the Fault, the bitterneſs of the Pain: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the length of the Fault, the length of the Pain: and according to the multiplicity of the Fault, the multiplicity of the Pain; as S. <hi>John</hi> preſcribes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. <hi>Do worthy fruits of Penance.</hi> For as particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Infirmities of the Body have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily particular Medicines, and no Medicine is of ſuch efficacy as that it can cure all Diſeaſes; ſo alſo ſpecial kinds of Sins have their ſpecial Penance: For Pride is not directly cured by Almſ-giving, nor Rancor and Envy by Prayer, nor Covetouſneſs by Faſting, nor Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity by Watching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But we directly ſatisfie for Pride by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:38619:123"/>for Avarice by giving of Alms, for Impurity, by the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtizement of the Fleſh with Hair-ſhirts and Diſciplines, for Gluttony by Faſting, for Talkativeneſs by Prayer, for Envy by Charity, and remiſſion of Injuries, for Rapine and unjuſt poſſeſſions, by Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But if any one, as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſays, cannot fulfill the whole Order of Satisfaction, then our bountiful Lord accepts of any other amends. Then for unjuſt things, Faſting ſuffices. If he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not faſt, Prayer ſuffices; and if for weakneſs he cannot pray, God is ſatisfied with a good will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> gives an Argument of falſe Repentance. It is a falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, when the Penitent leaves not an Office or Employment which he can by no means exerciſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sin; or if he bear hatred in his Heart; or if he do not ſatisfie
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:38619:124"/>every one whom he has offended; or if he do not pardon him who has offended him; or if he bear Arms againſt Juſtice. It is alſo a falſe Repentance, when one Sin is amended, and no care taken of another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XLII. <hi>Of Perſeverance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRUE Perſeverance is a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent exerciſe of Good Works, a continual ſtudy of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, a diligent conſervation of Spiritual Graces and Vertues unto Death. To this our Lord invites us in the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> 2. <hi>Be faithful unto Death, and I will give thee a crown of Life.</hi> This <hi>Job</hi> had, when he ſaid, <hi>Job</hi> 27. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil I dye. I will not depart from my innocency.</hi> And <hi>Tobias,</hi> who hid the Bodies of the
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:38619:124"/>dead in his houſe, and buried them in the night; although the King for this commanded him to be ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his Goods and kill'd. <hi>Tob.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>The exceeding great profit of Perſeverance, ought to induce us thereunto. For by this every good Work, and every Vertue ſhall be crowned, and our Salvation whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depends on it; according to that of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. <hi>He who ſhall perſevere to the end, ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Without this no Vertue or good Work is remunerable: Without this, all Perfection comes to nothing. For what did it profit the Apoſtle and Traytor <hi>Judas,</hi> that our Lord choſe him out of the World? what did profit him his long familiarity with Jeſus Chriſt? what the holy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons which he often heard from him? what the Examples, Virtues, and Miracles which he ſaw done by
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:38619:125"/>him? what the Society of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles? what the Grace beſtowed on him to preach and work Miracles? For to him, together with the other Apoſtles, he ſaid, <hi>Math.</hi> 10. <hi>Go, preach, ſaying, The Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is at hand; Cure the ſick, raiſe the dead, cure the leprous, caſt out Devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has an Argument of true Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance, who, neither for the love of Life, nor fear of Death; nor for threats, nor promiſes, departs from Virtue. As <hi>Suſanna,</hi> fearing not Death, ſaid, <hi>Dan.</hi> 13. <hi>If I do this,</hi> (that is, ſin) <hi>I muſt dye.</hi> And <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tathias,</hi> 1 Macchab. 2. <hi>Although all the Nations obey King Antiochus, and every one depart from the ſervice of the Law of his Fathers, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to his commands, I and my Sons and my brethren will obey the Law of our Fathers. God be propitious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> us.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="239" facs="tcp:38619:125"/>
               <p>He has an argument of falſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance, who falſly preſumes of his own Sanctity, that he cannot fall. Hence ariſes a freedom of Mind; hence he has no Watch over him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and ſo it is impoſſible for any Man perſevere in Sanctity. Even the very Apoſtles, if they were in the world, and not a watch over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſelves, they might fall. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Example in <hi>David,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Murder and Adulte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> was negligent in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Eyes, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="240" facs="tcp:38619:126"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall one day have all theſe Virtues more perfectly, than Humane Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing can comprehend. I confeſs to thee, O Lord, that he is happy at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and ſhall be more happy hereafter, who has theſe Virtues, in that perfection as they are here written; although per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps leſs may ſuffice to Salvation.</p>
               <p>I beſeech the alſo O Lord, with all the deſire of thy Son, and Holy Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Creatures, that thou wouldeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Diſcretion betwixt the Virtues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Nature, and Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> And whoſoever ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall hear of it, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mnipotent God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> one, true, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertain he who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> one, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:38619:126"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
